<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A disswasiue from poperie, containing twelve effectual reasons by vvhich every Papist, not wilfully blinded, may be brought to the truth, and euery Protestant confirmed in the same: written by Francis Dillingham Master of Arts, and fellow of Christs Colledge in Cambridge, necessarie for all men in these times.</title>
            <author>Dillingham, Francis, d. 1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6883</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111897</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847157</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847157</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12177</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20471)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12177)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 218:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A disswasiue from poperie, containing twelve effectual reasons by vvhich every Papist, not wilfully blinded, may be brought to the truth, and euery Protestant confirmed in the same: written by Francis Dillingham Master of Arts, and fellow of Christs Colledge in Cambridge, necessarie for all men in these times.</title>
                  <author>Dillingham, Francis, d. 1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 152 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legat, printer to the Vniversitie of Cambridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12177:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A <hi>Diſſwaſive</hi> FROM POPERIE, <hi>CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAINING TWELVE EFFECTVAL</hi> REASONS, BY VVHICH EVERY Papiſt, not wilfully blinded, may be brought to <hi>the truth, and euery Protestant confirmed</hi> in the ſame: written by <hi>Francis Dillin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gham Maſter of Arts, and fellow of</hi> Chriſts Colledge in Cambridge, <hi>neceſſarie for all men in</hi> theſe times.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Lactant. lib. de vero dei ſimulachro. cap. <hi>20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quid facies? maiores nè, an potiùs ratione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſequeris?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What will thou doer follow thy anceſtours or reaſon?</p>
            </q>
            <p>PRINTED BY IOHN LEGAT, <hi>Printer to the Vniuerſitie of Cambridge.</hi> 1599.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:12177:2"/>
            <head>The ſumme of the booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> The first reaſon of Antichrist.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> The ſecond of truth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> Of haereſie in generall.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> Of particular haereſies.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> Of popiſh diſſolute, and diſcomfortable do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> Of Idolatrie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> Of popiſh blasphemies.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> Of the Papists owne confeſsion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9</hi> The ninth, of the Practiſe of the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> Of Scripture.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11</hi> Of popiſh Contradictions.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12</hi> Of the originall of Poperie.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12177:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>TO THE</hi> right Honorable, and my <hi>very good Lord,</hi> Oliver <hi>L.</hi> S. Iohn, Baron of <hi>Bletſoe,</hi> Grace, and <hi>peace, with increaſe of</hi> honour, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>I is not vnknown (Right honourable and my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular good Lord) that man is not borne for himſelfe, but for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of others. To this principle agreeth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles precept,<note place="margin">Rom. 12. 1. Pet. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>that euery man according to his gift, ſhould indeauour himſelfe to do good.</hi> And to this precept, the practiſe of nature is anſwerable:<note place="margin">in Similitud.</note> 
               <hi>Vt luna</hi> (ſaith Eraſmus) <hi>quod lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis accepit à ſole mundo refundit: ita do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num à deo acceptum in commodum aliorum
<pb facs="tcp:12177:3"/> eſt conferendum. As the moone giueth that light to the world which it receiueth from the ſunne: ſo euery gift receiued from God ought to be beſtowed to the profit of others.</hi> All which excellent ſayings, are ſpoken of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery good, and therefore by conſequent of knowledge, of which <hi>Seneca</hi> writeth thus: <hi>Nulla me res delectabit licet eximia ſit, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mihi vnus ſciturus ſum. I delight not in any thing, which I my ſelfe know and none other.</hi> And againe: <hi>Nullius boni ſine ſocio iucunda poſſeſsio eſt. It is no pleaſure to poſſeſſe any good without a companion.</hi> The conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe and like ſpeaches, haue cauſed me to ſet pen to paper, againſt the myſticall and ſecret impietie of Popiſh religion, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though vnfit for ſo great a worke in many reſpects; as namely in regard of my health. For I may truly ſay with <hi>Seneca, Nulla mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi ſecura lux affulſit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jn Thebaid.</note> 
               <hi>I haue had no good day.</hi> This beeing a moſt certen truth, how vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble I am to vndergoe this buſines, the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude vſed by <hi>Tully</hi> may declare. <hi>Quemadmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſcalarum gradus ſi alios tollas, alios in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>s nonnullos malè haerentes relinquas, ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inae
<pb facs="tcp:12177:3"/> periculum ſtruas, non aſcenſum pares, ſic tot malis tùm victum, tùm fractum ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſcribendi quid dignum auribus, aut pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babile poteſt afferre. If thou take ſome rounds of the ladder away, and cut other, and leaue the rest looſe, thou endangereſt a downefall, and cauſest not an aſcenſion: ſo the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of writing beeing vanquiſhed with ſo many miſeries, what thing ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it bring forth worthie, and worth hearing and reading.</hi> This miſerie hath another attendant, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>pouertie</hi> and <hi>want,</hi> which (as one ſaith) is <hi>onus miſerum, &amp; grave,</hi> a woful and a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous burthen. The renowmed Philoſopher could ſay that felicity needed outward good things. For, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>It is impoſsible,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ethic.</hi> 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>or very hard for him that wanteth instruments, to doe any famous worke.</hi> But not too much of this matter, leaſt I ſeeme to be impatient, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelfe a preacher of patience. Onely this, I feare that the cauſe, why many are peruerted by Papiſts, and diuerted to pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, is the hope of preferment, which is not wanting in that religion. <hi>Sublatis ſtudio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb facs="tcp:12177:4"/> pretijs ipſa ſtudia pereunt,</hi> (ſaith Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius Tacitus) <hi>Take away the rewardes of learning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Annal. l. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and learning it ſelfe decaieth.</hi> But I leaue this complaint beeing a miſerie inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the deſpiſed eſtate of Gods Church in the ſight of the world, howſoeuer moſt glorious in the ſight of God. Thus (Right Honourable) you ſee the cauſe that moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me to ſet forth this treatiſe. Now in that I dedicate it vnto you, I haue many reaſons. For (to omit priuate reſpects, as namly your honourable and ſingular fauour towardes me, and all my friendes) ſuch is your deſire to further Chriſts kingdome, ſuch is your care of religion, your loue to learning, that for theſe cauſes you are moſt worthie of this dutie. And in theſe ſingular and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable graces of Gods ſpirit may you more reioyce then in any worldly thing. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> writeth) writte to <hi>Antipater</hi> concerning <hi>Alexander,</hi> that he ſhould not be proud becauſe of his kingdome, becauſe he that knewe God, hath as much cauſe as he: his meaning is this, that the knowledge of God is better then worldly honour.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12177:4"/>
            <p>The Lord bleſſe you and your wiſe, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and honourable Ladie with all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly and worldly honour.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your L. euer bounden Francis Dillingham.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:12177:5"/>
            <head>A preface to all Engliſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes whatſoeuer.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rhe. act. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not my purpoſe to vſe any long diſcourſe vnto you, that pleaſe your ſelues in the name of Papiſts, yet I pray you let me firſt craue an anſwer to this my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſiue, or els ſubmit your ſelues to gods truth. Secondly, I would bee certified vvhat ſhould cauſe you to continue in the Romiſh religion. Doth the vniuerſalitie of which you vvere wont to vaunt your ſelues? why then doe your Rhemiſts in their annotations vppon the <hi>20.</hi> chap. of the Reuel. proue the Pope not to bee Antichriſt, becauſe his kingdome is daily leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſened, and Antichrist during the time of his raigne ſhalbe greater then Chriſts flock? yea ſome of you haue vvritten that the Church in his time ſhall vtterly periſh as your ſelues know. Againe if vniuerſality chalketh out the church, why did the Arrian Emperour ſay to <hi>Liberius.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theodoret. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quota pars tu es orbis terrarum,
<pb facs="tcp:12177:5"/> qui ſolus facis cum homine ſcelerato, &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis terrarum, &amp; mundi totius pacem diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis? What part of the world art thou that onely takeſt part with the wicked man, and diſſolueſt the peace of the whole earth? Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius</hi> anſwereth, <hi>Non diminuitur ſolitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne mea verbum fidei, nam &amp; olim tres ſoli fuère qui edicto reſiſterent. In that I am left alone the word of faith is not diminiſhed, for in times paſt there were onely three that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted the kings edict.</hi> But it may be your vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is of ſome force with you; for your ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in this point, ſee my motiue of your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions. Alſo conſider that ther may be ſome diuerſitie of opinions in leſſer matters, and yet a true church, for els the auncient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhould haue beene no church, amongst whome there vvere many diſſentions, as you may ſee in the <hi>8.</hi> booke of the tripartite histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and <hi>12.</hi> chap. <hi>Themiſtius</hi> wrote to <hi>Valens</hi> that he ſhould not be cruell to the Chriſtians, <hi>Propter diſcordiam Eccleſiaſticorum dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matum: for the variance of Eccleſiaſtical opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</hi> For amongst the Pagans there vvere more then three hundred ſects. To come now
<pb facs="tcp:12177:6"/> to ſuccesſion, doth not <hi>Bellarmine</hi> your <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> teach that it prooueth not alwaies a church. Secondly, Atheiſts, Heretikes, Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and a woman haue beene Pope, and that interrupteth your ſucceſsion. Thirdly, your plurality of Popes, during your two and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſchiſmes diſanulleth the ſame. Laſtly, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Popes haue not beene Canonically elected. To proceed to antiquitie, ſee your ſelues ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of it in this my treatiſe: and yet you are not greatly vviſe men to alleadge bare anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie: for as <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſaieth in his <hi>2.</hi> booke and <hi>7.</hi> chap. <hi>Tanta eſt apud inſipientes autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas vetuſtatis, vt in cam inquirere ſcelus eſſe ducatur. Amongſt fooles antiquitie hath that authoritie, that it is counted a hainous thing to inquire into it.</hi> Laſtly concerning your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, I ſay with <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his book, <hi>de v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate Eccleſiae cap. 16.</hi> Let them not ſay it is true, becauſe <hi>Donatus,</hi> or <hi>Pontius,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man hath done theſe, &amp; theſe miracles: Againe, whether they hold the church or no let them ſhew, no otherwiſe, but by the Canonical bookes of holy Scriptures. I will not ſpend any time in painting out of the odious and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb facs="tcp:12177:6"/> lifes of Papiſts: but come to a concluſion namely that ſeing thoſe thinges that they were wont to bragge of, are taken from them, let them embrace the truth, let not the world ſeduce them againſt their owne conſciences. For what are vngodly rich men, but (as <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> ſaith) <hi>aſini ligna ferentes, aſſes bearing burdens.</hi> The Lord open your eyes to ſee the truth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12177:7"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I had many mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues to ſet forth this my trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe in latin, yet regarding the good of thoſe that are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in that tongue, I haue written it in Engliſh, with as much ſhortnes and breuitie as I could poſsibly. I confeſſe I might haue made a great volume of it, if I had inſiſted vpon the amplification of euery reaſon: but for diuerſe reſpects, I haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended it in this ſmall manuall. And as I haue diſſwaded men from popery by theſe twelve ſeuerall reaſons, ſo did I once thinke to haue adioyned more, but for cauſes known to my ſelfe, I haue yet concealed them. Their ſenſeleſſe paradoxes, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe arguments, with which their bookes are fraught, haue cauſed me ſo to abhorre their religion, that I may proteſt in ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a good conſcience, I could neuer read any argument to perſwade me to papiſtrie: yet haue I read their writers without any praeiudicate opinion at all, being neuer fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalled
<pb facs="tcp:12177:7"/> with this religion, in which through Gods grace nowe I ſtand. And Bellarmines corrupting of fathers, his fooliſh diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradictions with himſelfe, &amp; with other Papiſts, his ſenceleſſe ſophiſmes, his wreſting of holy writte, haue in them (as I thinke) this force to perſwade his readers from his religion. Now it remaineth (Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian reader) to deſire this of thee, to weigh theſe my motiues with an indifferent mind, and if thou receiueſt any good by them, to be thankefull to God, and to commend me in thy praiers vnto him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_authors">
            <pb facs="tcp:12177:8"/>
            <head>Catalogus authorum.</head>
            <list>
               <item>ALcoranus fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcanorum.</item>
               <item>Alexander de Ales.</item>
               <item>Alphonſus de caſtro.</item>
               <item>Ambroſius.</item>
               <item>Aquinas.</item>
               <item>Arias montanus.</item>
               <item>Arnobius.</item>
               <item>Auguſtinus.</item>
               <item>Bellarminus.</item>
               <item>Bernardus.</item>
               <item>Buckingerus.</item>
               <item>Catalogus teſtiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis.</item>
               <item>Cenſura Colonienſis.</item>
               <item>Catechiſmus Coloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis.</item>
               <item>Clemens Alexandri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</item>
               <item>Chryſoſthomus.</item>
               <item>Cuſanus.</item>
               <item>Cyprianus.</item>
               <item>Cyrillus Hieroſolymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus.</item>
               <item>Duraeus.</item>
               <item>Durandus.</item>
               <item>Epiphanius.</item>
               <item>Eraſmus.</item>
               <item>Euripides.</item>
               <item>Euſebius.</item>
               <item>Faſciculus temporum</item>
               <item>Freculphius.</item>
               <item>Gratianus.</item>
               <item>Gregorius Epiſcopus Romanus.</item>
               <item>Gregorius Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zenus.</item>
               <item>Gregorius Martinus.</item>
               <item>Hentenius.</item>
               <item>Herbranaus.</item>
               <item>Hierom.</item>
               <item>Hugo Cardinalis.</item>
               <item>Index Expurgatorius.</item>
               <item>Irenaeus.</item>
               <item>Iuellus.</item>
               <item>Iuſtinus.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:12177:8"/>
               <item>Lactantius.</item>
               <item>Lombardus.</item>
               <item>Lyra.</item>
               <item>Macrobius.</item>
               <item>Maierius.</item>
               <item>Mathaeus Paris.</item>
               <item>Melchior Canus.</item>
               <item>Origines.</item>
               <item>Picus Miranaula.</item>
               <item>Plautus.</item>
               <item>Polidorus Virgilius.</item>
               <item>Pſalterium Romanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
               <item>Rhemenſes.</item>
               <item>Roffenſis.</item>
               <item>Ruffinus.</item>
               <item>Scotus.</item>
               <item>Sleidan.</item>
               <item>Socrates.</item>
               <item>Tertullianus.</item>
               <item>Tullius.</item>
               <item>Turrianus.</item>
               <item>Wolfgangus Herma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</item>
               <item>Zozomenus.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="reason">
            <pb facs="tcp:12177:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12177:9"/>
            <head>THE FIRST REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>of Antichriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N times paſt (Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Reader) the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion was whether Chriſt appointed the Pope to be heade of this church, but now (bleſſed be God) it is not without cauſe demanded, whether he be Antichriſt or no. From which as the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>ſervus ſervorum,</hi> that is, the ſeruant of ſeruants, will not excuſe him, beeing indeed the title of curſed <hi>Cham,</hi> and ſo fit in Gods iuſt prouidence for the man of ſinne: ſo theſe circumſtances following beeing laide toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will firmely conclude the ſame.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>1.</hi> Circumſtance.</head>
               <p>Antichriſtianiſme is a myſterie, 2. Theſſ. cap. 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12177:10"/> that is, <hi>The myſterie of iniquity doth now worke:</hi> out of which place of holy writte, I argue, that neither the open blaſphemous haeretiks, nor the Turke can be that Antichriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are not diſſembled, but plaine and open enimies to Chriſt. Yet as Hierom ſaith on the 24. chapter of Mathew, <hi>Omnis Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiarchia eſt Antichriſtus.</hi> Euery Arch-hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritike is Antichriſt, but not Antichriſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, that ſingular Antichriſt. Maruell not then though all men perceiue &amp; vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him (namely the Pope) not to be that Antichriſt ſeeing it is a myſterie: for as fewe knowe the Goſpell becauſe it is a myſterie, ſo likewiſe little is the flocke to which this Antichriſt is revealed: pray therefore with Dauid to open thine eyes, that thou maiſt behold the ſecrets of God: for as Auguſtine ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſtola</hi> 11 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Qui didicerunt à Domino Ieſu eſſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miles &amp; mites in corde plus proficiunt or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do quàm audiendo &amp; legendo;</hi> that is, <hi>They that have learned of Chriſt meekeneſſe of minde, and humility of heart, profit more by prayer, then by hearing and reading.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:12177:10"/>
               <head>The ſecond Circumſtance.</head>
               <p>Antichriſt is not called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an aduerſary to God, although he doth band himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, an aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Chriſt in aemulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of like honour. For he arrogateth to himſelfe thoſe things that are propper to Chriſt, as namely remiſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes, which I prooue out of Bernard, who ſaith,<note place="margin">11. ſermon <hi>ad Milites.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Vnde ſcimus quòd Chriſtus poteſt dimit tere peccata? quia deus eſt. vnde ſcis quod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us eſt? miracula probant.</hi> That is, <hi>Howe do we knowe that Chriſt can remit ſinnes? becauſe he is God. How dost thou knowe he is God? his miracles prooue the ſame.</hi> Out of which te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony I frame this ſyllogiſme: he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth ſinnes is god: but the pope remineth ſinnes, therefore he is god: and by conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Antichriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third Circumſtance.</head>
               <p>Thoſe things which the Papiſts write concerning Antichriſt are ridiculous. Firſt the Rhemiſts ſay and affirme that he ſhall come of the tribe of Dan, which opinion Bellarmine ſtrongly refuteth by this reaſon: Namely, becauſe the tribes are ſo confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12177:11"/> that no man can ſay this man is of this or that Tribe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, they ſay Antichriſt ſhall be the Iewes Meſsias, but he muſt ſpring of the tribe of Iudah: <hi>ergo,</hi> Antichriſt the Iewes Meſsias cannot deſcend of Dan.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, they teach he ſhall be one ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler man, which is vnpoſsible: for it is written in the ſecond to the Theſ. 2. cap. verſ. 7. <hi>The myſterie of iniquity now worketh,</hi> but he that worketh from that time till the comming of Chriſt is no ſingular man: <hi>ergo</hi> Antichriſt is not one ſingular man.</p>
               <p>The further proofe of this, that he is not one ſingular man, Saint Iohn ſaith: 1. Ioh. 2.22. <hi>Who is a liar but he that denyeth that Ieſus is Christ: the ſame is Antichriſt that denieth the father and the ſonne: euery one that denieth the ſonne hath not the father.</hi> This note as it doth agree to all haeretiks, ſo principally to the Pope, who denieth the offices of Chriſt, as other haeretickes haue done his perſon. Read the 2. of Iohn and the 7. verſe: alſo the 4. of Iohn &amp; the thrid verſe, Ireneus ſaith it is a kingdom. <hi>Lib.</hi> 5.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:12177:11"/>
               <p>Fourthly, they teach that he ſhall raigne but three yeres and a halfe, which Henteni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us a papiſt in his preface to his tranſlation of Arethas ouerthroweth, ſaying, <hi>it is unpoſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that Antichriſt in ſo ſhort time ſhould ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſo many kingdomes and provinces.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly Chriſt his comming to iudgement ſhall be known ſo ſoone as Antichriſt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed, for if he ſhall be ſlaine of Chriſt, then it will be eaſie to caſt the time of three yeres &amp; a halfe, &amp; ſo conſequently to tell the very houre of Chriſt his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to iudgement.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, they teach he ſhall ſit at Hieruſalem which is ouerthrowen and is not eaſily ree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dified. 2. it cannot be called the temple of God. 3. The Rhemiſtes themſelues out of Auguſtine encline to thinke that he ſhall not ſit there: but more of this in the 4. circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth circumſtance.</head>
               <p>Antichriſt ſhall ſit in the Church of God, 2. Theſſ. 2. cap. verſ. 4. So ſaith ſaith ſaint Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom. <hi>Antichristus ſedebit in Eccleſia Dei.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">11. Epiſt. quae. alga.</note> 
                  <hi>Antichrist ſhall ſit in the church of God,</hi> not in the true Church, but that which is ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, by which the argument of Bellarmine is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12177:12"/> anſwered, who goeth about to prooue by this circumſtance that the church of Rome is the true church.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>5.</hi> Circumſtance.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gregorius lib. <hi>4.</hi> epis. <hi>34.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Quicunque ſe vniuerſalem Epiſcopum ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellat is Antichriſtus est. Papa vniuerſalem Epiſcopum ſe appellat: ergo.</hi> whoſoeuer cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth himſelfe vniuerſall Biſhop, hee is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, but ſo doth the Pope. <hi>Ergo.</hi> And leaſt they ſhould anſwere, that the propoſition is not to bee vnderſtood of the Biſhop of Rome, heare what Gregory ſaith: <hi>Eſt nomen blaſphemiae,</hi> it is a name of blaſphemie: And again <hi>Petrus non vocatur vniuerſalis Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus.</hi> Peter is not called vniuerſall Biſhop.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>6.</hi> circumstance.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">In his 38. demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>Antichriſt ſhall ſit at Rome, ſo doeth San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders confeſſe, and the Rhemiſts doe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict this in their Annotations vpon the 5. ver. of the 11. chap. of the Revelation: for the proofe of which I thus ioyne in argument with them. 1. That which was Babilon in S. Iohns time is the ſame that he prophecieth to be the chiefe ſeat of Antichriſt: but Rome was then Babylon: <hi>Ergo</hi> it is the ſame that he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12177:12"/> prophecieth to bee the chiefe ſeate of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt. 2 The fathers affirme Rome to be Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon when they wrote: out of which thus I conclude. In the dayes of the Fathers <hi>viz.</hi> Auguſtine, Hierome, &amp;c. Rome was not heatheniſh, but by them it is called the ſeat of Antichriſt, <hi>Ergo</hi> not heatheniſh Rome is the ſeat of Antichriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>7</hi> Circumstance.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Papa diſpenſat contra verbum Dei.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gratian. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar. <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>76.</hi>
                  </note> The Pope diſpenſeth againſt Gods word: Again, <hi>Praecepta moralia ſunt per Eccleſiam muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilia.</hi> The morall praecepts may bee altered by the church. Further he maymeth the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament in taking the cup from the people, yea the Sacrament which he pretendeth to honour as God is carried before him on an hackney when he rideth on mens ſhoulders: his throne is alſo aboue the altar. In the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilie he beateth open the gates of Paradiſe with a golden hammer. The croſſe honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with diuine honour is caſt at his feete, out of which I conclude he exalteth himſelf aboue God, or at leaſt wiſe maketh himſelfe equall to God: for no lawe can bee diſpenſed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12177:13"/> with al, but by the ſame authoritie by which it was made, or by a greater.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>8.</hi> Circumstance.</head>
               <p>In the time of Antichriſt there ſhalbe a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall departure from the faith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rhem. in the</hi> 2. Theſſ. 2.7.</note> ſo doe the Papiſts themſelues confeſſe. Nowe let vs ſee whether this Apoſtaſie doeth agree to them or no. To decide this controuerſie who is better then Saint Paule who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecieth of thappoſtaſie. The ſame Apoſtle in the firſt to Timothie, and fourth chapter giueth ſuch euident ſignes &amp; notes as agree properly vnto them, for they forbid meates and mariages in hypocriſie, other heretikes in open blaſphemie: well ſaieth Saint Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome vpon the eleuenth of Daniel: <hi>Nota est Antichristi prohibere nuptias. It is a note of Antichrist to forbid mariages.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>9.</hi> Circumstance.</head>
               <p>The ninth Circumſtance is taken out of the 13. of the Revel. from the eleuenth verſe, and ſo forward. Hee is Antichriſt that hath two hornes like a lamb, and ſpeaketh like a dragon: Againe he that cauſeth the earth to worſhipp the firſt beaſt is Antichriſt, alſo he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12177:13"/> that doeth worke wonders is Antichriſt, with many moe notes and marks, that there follow: but all theſe doth the Pope, <hi>Ergo</hi> he is Antichriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>10.</hi> Circumſtance.</head>
               <p>Antichriſt is called 2. Theſſ. 2. cap. 3. v. <hi>The man of ſin:</hi> which fitly agreeth to the Pope, for what monſters of men haue bin Popes. Silveſter was made Pope by the help of the diuell. <hi>Auxilio diaboli factus est Papa.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>71:</hi> Faſc. Tem.</note> Iohn the twelth abuſed his fathers concubine, gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded one of his Cardinalls, drank to the diuel, and at dice called for help of Iupiter and Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. Boniface the ſeuenth robbed S. Peters church of al the iewells and pretious things. Read their owne ſtories becauſe I purpoſe breuitie.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 1166. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1168.</note> Matthew Paris monke of Saint Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bons recordeth that the biſhop of Lincolne proued the Pope to bee Antichriſt by this reaſon and writeth thus.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Eius auaritiae totus non ſufficit orbis,</l>
                  <l>Eius luxuriae meretrixnon ſufficit omnis.</l>
               </q>
               <p>That is to ſaye, <hi>The Popes couetouſnes and whoredome are not ſatisfied with the whole
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12177:14"/> world.</hi> To come therefore to a concluſion, I deſire thee (chriſtian Reader) to laye all theſe circumſtances together and ſo to conclude this matter in queſtion whether the Pope be Antichriſt or no: doe not looſely of any one gather any thing, but binde them togither and then there will bee not a three-fold but a tenne-folde corde, which is not eaſily bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="reason">
            <head>The ſecond reaſon of truth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N handling this motion or reaſon it is not my purpoſe to define or to diſtinguiſh truth, but brie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flie to ſet downe ſome properties of the ſame which cannot poſsibly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to Poperie, onely I deſire thee (chriſtian Reader) to pray to Chriſt who is truth that thou mayeſt conceaue and embrace it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:12177:14"/>
               <head>The first propertie.</head>
               <p>Truth hath this propertie, that it is ſimple, and needeth not many interpretations and expoſitions: ſo ſaith <hi>Euripides,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But Poperie to defende it ſelfe vſeth many expoſitions,<note place="margin">Vide rever. Bilſon. de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram.</note> and yet knoweth not what to hold. For the proofe of this, conſider their interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the firſt word in this ſhort ſentence: <hi>this is my bodie.</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">contra Plo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>retum lib. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Gerſon</hi> affirmeth that it ſignifieth the ſubſtance of bread, and<note n="e" place="margin">contra Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolic. ſophiſt</note> 
                  <hi>Steuen Gardiner</hi> ſometimes thought ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: notwithſtanding afterward he changed his minde, and came to <hi>Individuum vagum,</hi> as if Chriſt had ſaide, <hi>This</hi> (what it is I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell, but it muſt needes be ſomewhat) <hi>is my bodie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">in <hi>4.</hi> of Sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> diſt. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Occam</hi> and other ſay the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noune <hi>this,</hi> muſt be referred to the bodie of Chriſt, as if our Sauiour had ſaide, This my bodie is my bodie.<note place="margin">de Conſe. diſt. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> Their gloſſe reſolueth this queſtion on this manner. <hi>Solet quaeri quid demonstretur per pronomen, Hoc. It is a common question what is meant by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noune, This.</hi> To this demand I ſay nothing is meant, but it is there put materially without
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12177:15"/> any ſignification at all: thus they turned and toſſed the words of Chriſt, till they brought all that the Lord ſaid at his laſt ſupper to plaine nothing.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tomo</hi> 2.</note> Duraeus and Bellarmine teach that by the word <hi>(this)</hi> is meant the whole ſubſtance which Chriſt had in his hand. I demande then what this ſubſtance was, whether it was bread, or the body of Chriſt; if bread, then there was a figure, if the body of Chriſt, then there muſt be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation before theſe wordes were pronounced, which plainely fighteth with their fancies. This propertie being cleerely auouched, if it pleaſe thee to conſider (gentle reader) the Calueniſts expoſitions (as they call them) thou ſhalt find them to be all one: namely <hi>this</hi> ſignifieth, or <hi>this</hi> is a ſigne of my body: let Caroloſtadius and the Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans anſwer for themſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond propertie.</head>
               <p>The ſecond propertie of truth is that it bluſheth to be hid,<note place="margin">Lib. aduerſus Valen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſo ſaith Tertullian, <hi>Nihil veritas erube ſcit niſi ſolummodo abſcondi,</hi> that is, <hi>truth is aſhamed of nothing but of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 10.27</note> and our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12177:15"/> I ſhew you preach on the houſe toppes:</hi> but they hid their traditions from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as Bellarmine himſelfe confeſſeth, which argueth that they were not truth. I will not here confute his anſwer to the ſaying of our Sauiour Chriſt, becauſe I ſhall deale with it in the Motiue of Haereſies. If they retort this propertie againſt vs becauſe our Church was [as they call it] <hi>occulta,</hi> that is, hid for many yeres; I firſt anſwer, that they muſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betwixt the time of peace and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution:<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> truth in perſecution may be driuen into the wilderneſſe, but in peace who kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth not, but that it ought plainely to be taught. Secondly I anſwer that the Papiſts haue alwaies felt our Church (as teſtifieth Reinerus a popiſh Inquiſitour,<note place="margin">Catolog. teſt. veri.</note>) &amp; ſo I paſſe to the 3. propertie of truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third propertie.</head>
               <p>The third propertie of truth is, that it is <hi>magna &amp; praevalet,</hi> it is great and preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth: reade the third of Eſdras for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of this, where trueth is proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſtronger then wine and women; and indeede Actes the fift and 39. If it be of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12177:16"/> God, it cannot be deſtroied: this declareth then moſt apparantly, that it could not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede but of ſome diuine power and ſuper-naturall aſsiſtance, that amidſt the contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and oppoſitions of ſo many adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, among the whippes, ſwordes, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, of ſo bloodie and cruell Caniballs as the Papiſts are, our poore, ſimple, and feeble congregation ſhould peirce through and augment it ſelfe ſtrongly, eſpecially if we conſider the outward means of this increaſe where there was nothing to allure or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t mans nature, nothing gorgeous, nothing delectable, nothing to pleaſe or entertaine ſenſualitie: by which is anſwered their cauil, that trueth reſteth with them becauſe of their great multitudes, for had they not had murthers,<note place="margin">Revel. 9.21.</note> ſorceries, fornication, and thefts, (which are as I will prooue (God willing) foure pillars of papiſtrie) they had neuer come to that primarie: yea who knoweth not that with Cyrus they powre forth Gold to their ſlauiſh ſect by heaps and waight, and not by number and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:12177:16"/>
               <head>The fourth property.</head>
               <p>The fourth propertie of trueth is to be ſteadfaſt and perpetually like it ſelfe, for which cauſe in the Hebrew tongue it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Emeth</hi> of the roote which ſignifieth ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, ſo doe the Latines call that <hi>verum</hi> which is immutabile, <hi>&amp; per omnia ſibi ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le,</hi> immutable and like it ſelfe euery way: but in popery there is no ſteadfaſtneſſe; is not <hi>prima &amp; ſecunda iuſtificatio,</hi> the firſt and ſecond iuſtification a new deuiſe?<note place="margin">Cenſura col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon. Ex con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilio Triden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti.</note> can any Papiſt reſolue the certenty of Peters ſitting at Roome: read Bellarmine, here he diſagre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from Onuphrius, and Onuphrius from the reſt of the Papiſts in this point, which is the foundation of Poperie: &amp; is the greateſt point of Papiſtrie ſo vncertaine that they knowe not what to hold? Doth not Allen confeſſe in his booke of purgatorie, that there is no text brought to prooue the ſame which might not be otherwiſe applyed? Nay haue not the Rhemiſts and Bellarmine himſelfe left ſchoole conceipts, and brought in their owne deuiſes, witneſſe their owne writing. Tell me thou learned Catholike
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12177:17"/> who ſucceeded Peter? Tertullian affirmeth, that <hi>Petrus Clementem Epiſcopum Romano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ordinauit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. de praeſ.</note> that Peter ordained Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Biſhop of Rome.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 3.</note> Ireneus placeth next to Peter, Linus, Ancletus, and then Clement. Read Hierom and Auguſtine, and thou ſhalt finde greater diuerſitie. Anſwere me papiſt, howe or with what kinde of worſhip Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are to be honoured, Bellarmine himſelfe is not aſſured of this point, as thou maieſt read in his tractate of Images. Laſtly, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I cannot be long) anſwere me howe Saints heare our prayers if thou canſt: Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelfe muſt needes yeeld to thee, for he is ignorant of that point, &amp; therefore an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth vncertainties, as he doeth in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe of purgatorie beeing preſſed with Theophilactes authority, now making it a part of the hande of God which is a place of all iuſt mens ſoules: and in the next wordes a part of hel. Thus Chriſtian reader like wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering trauellers out of the way, the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedſt papiſts knowe not where to reſt: yea like drunkards they ſtagger to and fro, but thankes be to God it is not ſo with the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiniſts
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12177:17"/> who coyne no new diſtinctions, for truth is alwaies the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>5.</hi> propertie.</head>
               <p>The 5. propertie of truth is that it is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to perſecution, <hi>Obſequium amicos veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas odium parit. Friends are the children of flatterie, &amp; hatred is begotten by harmeleſſe truth.</hi> Peruſe the whole booke of God, nay all hiſtories and thou ſhalt finde this thing moſt clearely confirmed: what then cauſed Bellarmine to teach that temporall proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is a note of the church: Chriſt and his Apoſtles are much beholding to him, who ſuffred exquiſite torments and therefore by his diuinitie are to bee exempted from the number of Gods Saints, but they that haue better learned Chriſt hold otherwiſe. Now to returne to the matter,<note place="margin">Read the booke of Martyrs.</note> haue not the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts bin drunken with the blood of Gods Saints: ſo I come to the ſixt and laſt property of truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>6.</hi> Propertie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Idverum quodcunque primum, id adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinum quodcunque poſterius:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertullian adv. Prax.</note> 
                  <hi>That is true which is firſt, that is adulterous which is an
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12177:18"/> after intention:</hi> but their opinions are not firſt but latter deuiſes: did not the lay people receiue the cup in the Apoſtles time, no Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt although he hath loſt his forehead can denie it. To wind this vp in a word: Maſter Iewell (that reuerend and renowned biſhop his challenge in the 27. articles is not anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>Totis iam triginta annis Catholici om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Iuello nostro nondum fatisfecerunt,</hi> that is, <hi>All the Papiſts in thirtie yeeres ſpace and vpvvard haue not ſatisfied M. Iewell.</hi> And therefore I conſtantly conclude all theſe 27. opinions are new and no auncient doctrine thus: they that cannot ſhew 27. of their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in the compaſſe of ſix hundred yeares are mainteiners of new doctrin: but the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts cannot do this: therfore they maintaine a new doctrine and by conſequence a falſe doctrine. Now as in the former circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Antichriſt, ſo likewiſe in theſe ſixe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall notes of truth, I deſire thee to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; thou maiſt be able to maintaine this, that truth is not lodged in the Popes breaſt.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="reason">
            <pb facs="tcp:12177:18"/>
            <head>The third reaſon of hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy in generall.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S touching the definition of haereſie, I might ſpend many wordes and much time,<note place="margin">Lib. de veili ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e cred.</note> but I referre thee to Auguſtine, &amp; come to particular notes and markes of haeretickes, which I doubt not but moſt euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to prooue that they agree to papiſts after a kind of Excellencie,<note place="margin">Ariſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Metap.</note> for ſo I haue learned to ſpeake by metaphyſicall phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The firſt note.</head>
               <p>The firſt note or badge of haereticks is to mayme the ſayings of Fathers.<note place="margin">Counc. <hi>8.</hi> Conſtant Juelius act. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> The eight Counſell of Conſtantinople and the eight act hath theſe wordes. <hi>Non conuenit ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxis ita circumtruncat as ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctorum patru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> voces deflorare haereticorum potius hoc pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prium est. Is it not meete to mayme the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Fathers, it is the point of haeretiks to doe ſo.</hi> That the Papiſts doe mayme the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12177:19"/> of Fathers, I might ſhewe by many examples. Duraeus in his tenth page citing Auguſtine his teſtimony out of his booke <hi>de fide &amp; operibus,</hi> and the 14. chap. leaueth out theſe words which plainely ouerthrow his defence: namely, <hi>opera ſequu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum non praecedunt iustificandum,</hi> that is <hi>Works follow him that is iuſtified, they go not before iuſtification.</hi> Harding ſo dealeth with the teſtimony of Gregorie in the article of the popes primacy: but I will conuince them by their owne teſtimony, out of their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex expurgatorius,</hi> page 11. <hi>Although (ſay they) we make no great account of this booke viz. Bertramius and therefore we would not greatly care, if either it were no where ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, or vtterly loſt yet ſeeing that in other ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Catholik writers we beare very many errors &amp; extenuate, &amp; excuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea very often by deviſing ſome pretie ſhift we denie them, and doe faine ſome commodious ſence vnto them, when they are oppoſed againſt vs in diſputations, or in Conflicts with the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, we doe not ſee why Bertram doth not deſerue the ſame equity.</hi> Thus farre the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12177:19"/> papiſts themſelues, whoſe owne words de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that they are voide of al truth and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie. What ſhould I ſpeake of Cyprian, who to eſtabliſh Peters primacy is falſified by Pamelius contrarie to the auncient editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in print, yea the very argument of the place is directly contrary vnto it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond note.</head>
               <p>The ſecond note of Haeretickes is, not to ſtand to onely ſcriptures, ſo ſaith Tertullian, <hi>aufer haereticis quae cum ethnicis ſapiunt, vt de ſcripturis ſolis quaeſtiones ſuas ſistant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. de reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect. carnis.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; ſtare non poterunt: take from the haeretickes that which is common to the heathen with them, that they propound their queſtions on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of ſcripture and they cannot ſtande.</hi> Out of which teſtimony I reaſon thus: they that diſpute not out of ſcripture alone, are either haeretickes or Ethnickes, but the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts do no ſo diſpute: <hi>Ergo</hi> they are either Haeretickes or Ethnickes. I will conclude this propertie with the Hiſtorie recorded by Maſter Sleidon in his ſixt booke at the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12177:20"/> diſputation at Berne, when Conradus Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerus an Auguſtinian prooued that he muſt diſpute out of nothing but ſcripture, he by and by fled, and ſo in that place poperie was deſtroyed: ſo Lord, let papiſtrie periſh in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third note.</head>
               <p>The third note of haeretickes is to accuſe the ſcripture of vncertainty. <hi>Haereticks</hi> (ſaith Iraeneus) <hi>cum ex ſcripturis arguu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſationem ipſarum ſcipturarum conuertu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quaſi varie ſunt dictae: &amp; quia non poſsit ex his inveniri veritas, ab bijs qui ne ſciant traditionem, non enim per literas traditam illam ſed per vivam vocem &amp;c. When they are convicted out of the ſcriptures, they fall to accuſing of the ſcriptures themſelues, as though they were diuerſly vttered, and that the trueth could not be found out of them which knowe not the traditon, for that was not deliuered in writing, but by word of mouth.</hi> Beſids in the ſame place he hath theſe wordes: they accuſe the ſcriptures, <hi>quaſi non rectè ſe habent, neque ſunt ex authoritate, as though they were not right an a perfect, or
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12177:20"/> not of authority ſufficient.</hi> Whether the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts hold not all theſe points mencioned, I appeale to their own conſcience, though I knowe it to be corrupt. Did not Sylueſter affirme that,<note place="margin">Sleidan. lib. <hi>1.</hi> fol. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ab authoritate papae vis omnis ſcripturae pendet, all the authority of the ſcripture dependeth on the pope?</hi> Doth not Cuſanus write that the ſcriptures <hi>vna cum tempore mutantur, are chaunged with time?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt <hi>2.</hi> vid. Whitak. cont. Durae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. p. <hi>161</hi> &amp; <hi>117.</hi>
                  </note> Who but Wolfangus Herma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nus blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that the ſcriptures without the church, are of no more worth then Aeſops fables? and as touching traditions do not they teach that we haue not the fence of holy writ, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we doe not embrace the truth of their traditions? ſo then gather of all theſe that they are haeretikes, as well as thoſe againſt whome Iraeneus did write.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth note.</head>
               <p>The fourth note is to conceale their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine from the people, <hi>dicunt</hi> (as teſtifieth I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeneus) <hi>no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> opportere ip ſorum mysteria effae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, ſed in abſcondito contineri per ſilentium:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 23.</note> 
                  <hi>They affirme that their myſteries and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets are not to be vttered, but to be concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:12177:21"/> which is directly contrarie to our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt his wordes,<note place="margin">Matt. 10.27.</note> who commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thoſe thinges which he taught to be publiſhed on the houſe toppes, to which place Bellarmine anſwereth, <hi>ſi opus eſt if it be needefull.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">de tradit.</note> I doubt not but if he had beene furniſhed with a better anſwer, we ſhould haue had it, but pardon errour which hath but figge leaues to hide her filthineſſe: may not the Atheiſt ſay, when he is commanded to beleeue, and keepe gods commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, <hi>ſi opus est, If it be requiſite I will doe them.</hi> To ſhewe nowe that the papiſts conceale their ſecrets from the people is needeleſſe, ſeeing it is confeſſed by Bellarmine in his tractate of Traditions. And why is their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in an vnknown tongue? why are the ſcriptures forbidden the laye people,<note place="margin">Clem. Alex. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> but to hide their errors: ſo that I may fitly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare the Romiſh religion to the temples of Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, which without were deckt with gold, but within had moſt loathſome ſights.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>5.</hi> note</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The fift note is, to vaunte and to boaſt themſelues of their pretended and falſely cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12177:21"/> knowledge, 1. Tim. 6.20.</hi> dicunt ſe <hi>[ſaith Iraeneus]</hi> non ſolum preſbyteris,<note place="margin">Lib.</note> ſed etiam Apoſtolis exiſtentes ſapientiores ſynceram inveniſſe veritatem: they ſay that beeing wiſer then the auncient and Apoſtles, they haue found out the ſyncere truth.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>This note is ſo euidently eminent in all haereticks that the Rhemiſts themſelues haue made made it a badge of an haereticke; but howe ſhall we prooue that the papiſts like empty veſſels make the lowdeſt &amp; the greateſt ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>The maker of their Apologie doth it for me ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance their fellowes in this inſolent ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner.</hi> Our wits, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> are from God in as plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full manner as theirs, our foundation in all kinde of faculties requiſite for the studie of Diuinitie is as deeply laid as theirs; our dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence rather more then theirs: our times both for age and studie more complete, then theirs commonly can be: Our order, method, and courſe of Diuinity much more profitable then theirs: we haue more diſputations, leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, conferences, examinations, repetitions inſtructions, catechizings, reſolutions of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes both of conſcience, and controuerſie: me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12177:22"/> and manners to proceed to the conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the deceiued, and ſuch like exerciſes in our two Colledges, then they in their two Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities containing neere hand <hi>30.</hi> goodly Colledges, as for the Masters and Profeſſours in our Colledges ſpecially the Romane rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, we may be bold to ſay they be in all kinde the most choyſe and cunning men in al Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome for vertue, learning, &amp;c. <hi>Would not this odious and arrogant compariſon rather beſeeme boies in the ſchoole, then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines in the church: thus the Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues haue made both the propoſition and aſſumption, ſo that if ſo bee they bee not wilfully blinde, they may inferre the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Tht <hi>6.</hi> Note.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The 6. note is to refuſe the common name of Chriſtians and to chooſe themſelues ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall names. Hierom</hi> in dialogo contra Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifir: Sicubi audiueris eos qui dicuntur Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti non à domino Ieſu ſed ab alio nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupari, vt puta Marcionitas, Valentinianos, ſcito non Eccleſiam Christi eſſe ſed Antichriſti ſyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogam. If thou hearest any where ſuch as bee
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12177:22"/> ſaid to be of Christ, not to haue their names of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt (as Marcionites, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinians,) knowe thou that they belong not to the Church of Chriſt, but to the ſynagoge of Antichriſt. <hi>Haue not the Papiſts peculiar names as Dominicans, Franciſcans, Ieſuites, Thomiſtes and Scotiſtes maintaining al one grand hereſie of Poperie: yet hauing their diuerſe opinions among themſelues &amp; each ſect enuying other, and ſwelling againſt the other, which cauſed Anſelmus as Heerbran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus reporteth to break out into this ſpeach.</hi> Quis non contemnat religionem tot varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus ſubiectam: Who would not deſpiſe a religion ſubiect to ſo many ſects.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>7.</hi> Note.</head>
               <p>The heretikes in all ages haue by allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries vpholden their errours, and allegories haue bin their ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt inſtruments to work withall. Epiphanius maketh mention of a beaſtly kinde of heretikes, who by allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries defended the ſinne of the Sodomites not onely as a thing that might be ſuffred, but as a duetie that muſt be done, moſt ſhamefully racking to the defence of that ſhameles opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12177:23"/> theſe wordes of Chriſt. <hi>Verely I ſay vnto thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 5.26.</note> 
                  <hi>thou ſhalt not come out thence till thou haſt paid the vttermoſt farthing</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that is, <hi>they ſay that what ſoeuer are thought euill amongst men, are not euill indeed, but naturally good, for nothing is naturally euill.</hi> The heretiks called <hi>Priſcillianiſtae</hi> did auoid by allegorizing whatſoeuer was brought againſt them,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de Haere.</note> 
                  <hi>In ſuos ſenſus allegorizando vertunt quicquid in ſanctis libris est quod eorum euertat errorem: vvhatſoeuer is found in the Scripture that ouerthrovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth their errours, by an allegoricall expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition they make it to maintaine the ſame.</hi> So do the Anabaptiſtes and Familiſtes now in our daies. As for the Papiſtes haue not they plucked their purgatorie out of the ſame text aboue named by an Allegorie? Doe not they prooue their free-will by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legorizing the parable in the tenth chapter of S. Luke, which is concerning the man halfe dead. By which wee ſee it common to heretikes and not peculiar to any one
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12177:23"/> by allegories to abuſe the holie Scriptures, to be abbetors of their abſurdities. Many moe places might I haue alleadged out of the Papiſtes to prooue this,<note place="margin">Vide Dur. de ſopiſ.</note> but the trueth is ſo cleare and manifeſt that they cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>8.</hi> Note.</head>
               <p>The eight note is to enioyne the lay peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thoſe things that are to bee performed by the Miniſters.<note place="margin">Tertul lib. de praeſcrip.</note> 
                  <hi>Laicis ſacerdotalia in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iungunt; ipſae mulieres haereticae quàm pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caces quae audent tingere, ordinationes eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum leues &amp; inconſtantes &amp;c. they command the people priests, duties, their women are ſo bold as to baptize, their ordinations of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters are light and inconstant.</hi> Theſe properties doe liuely paint out the Papiſtes. Their Mid-wiues vſe to baptize, their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and conſecrations are they not of the baſeſt of the people. I would wee had not had experience of this curſed practiſe of Ieroboam.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Ordo ſacerdotum fatuo turbatur ab omni:</l>
                  <l>Labitur, &amp; paſſim Religionis honos.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Euery foole with the Papiſts are prieſted,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12177:24"/> by which religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commeth to ruine, nay I dare avouch, that they haue conſecrated ſhriuelings that are not borne <hi>ad Aram,</hi> but <hi>ad Haram,</hi> not to ſerue at the altar, but at the ſwine-ſtie. Here I might haue added moe properties of heretiks confeſſed by the Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts themſelues,<note place="margin">Vpon Iud.</note> as contempt of authoritie, the crueltie of Cain, the couetouſnes of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam, which aptly agree to the Papiſts: for the Pope will be ſubiect to none, no not to a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councell: witneſſe Martine the 5. and Eugenius the 4. who would not ſtand to the decrees of the Councels of Conſtance, and Baſill. As touching murthers the ſtreetes haue ouerflowen with the blood of Gods Saints: For couetouſneſſe let Eraſmus ſpeake <hi>Chiliad.</hi> 1. <hi>Cent.</hi> 9.12. <hi>Non datur Baptiſmus, non licet fieri Christianum niſi numeres, non comprobant Matrimonium niſinumeres, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> audiunt poenitentium confesſiones, niſi ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent praemium: ſacrificant co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducti, non pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt gratis, non orant gratis: non impertiunt corpus Chriſti, niſi numeres: quin vendunt ſepulturam, idque in alieno ſolo.</hi> In Engliſh it is thus much. <hi>It is not lawfull for thee to be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12177:24"/> baptized except thou pay: Matrimonie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out money is not ratified: the Confeſſours heare no Confesſions without reward:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">O inexplebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem auaritia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
                  <hi>they ſacrifice for hire: they neither ſing, nor pray, nor giue names freely: No they will not mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster the Sacrament without wages: they ſell ſepulchres in another mans ſoyle.</hi> O the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding dropſie of couetouſnes:<note place="margin">Aulular.</note> may I not cry out with Plautus. <hi>Tenaces dominos no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra aetas tulit, quos Harpagonas, Harpyas, Tantalos appellare ſoleo, in medio Oceani gurgite ſitibundos: Non Midae, non Craeſi, non omnis Per ſarum copia tartaream eorum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gluviem explere potest. This age hath grip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Lords (which I am accuſtomed to cal Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagons,</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Theſe were Monſters.</note> 
                  <hi>Harpyes, Tantaluſſes thirſtie in the midſt of the Ocean ſea: their helliſh gorge is not ſatisfied with the money of Midas, with the coyne of Craeſus, nor with the pomp of the Perſians.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ob.</note> But they will here obiect that they haue not beene condemned by any generall Councell, and therfore are not for theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties (though all laid togither) to be accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted heretikes:<note place="margin">Sol.</note> which obiection how friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous it is, I hope to make manifeſt. Were
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12177:25"/> the heretikes in thappoſtles time condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by a general Councell? they might haue defended the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues by this obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſwel as the Papiſtes. Ebion and Cerinthus againſt whome Saint Iohn wrote his goſpell, who dare denie them to be heretikes? Tertullian in his booke <hi>de praeſcriptione,</hi> and Irenaeus <hi>aduerſus haereſes</hi> mention multitudes of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies not then condemned by any generall Councell. I dare not alleadge the authoritie of Iewes who call the Chriſtians <hi>minim and cophrim bagnikkar:</hi> that is, <hi>Heretikes and denying the foundation,</hi> though not condemned by a generall Councell, leaſt they accuſe me of Iudaiſme as they doe the Proteſtants, becauſe wee doe denie Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
               <p>Laſtly how can it bee of the eſſence of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie to be condemned by a generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, ſeing as Auguſtine confeſſeth that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer plenarie Councels may be amended by latter, which muſt needs bee vnderſtood of errour: for the condition which Saint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine repeateth in the firſt endureth to the laſt. <hi>Si quid fortè à veritate deuiatum est. If
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12177:25"/> in ought they ſwerue from the truth,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept that be vnderſtood he anſwereth not the thing that was obiected by the Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes: they oppoſed the Councell of Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an in a matter of doctrine not of diſcipline, S. Auguſtine replieth Biſhops might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued and ſo might Councels, in what then but in matters of doctrine? And ſo I proceed to the fourth Reaſon taken from particular hereſies: with this admonition that this was the verie obiection of the Pelagians as may be ſeene in Auguſtine <hi>tomo</hi> 7. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>contra duas epis. Pelag. in fine libri:</hi> to whome hee anſwereth, <hi>Quaſi nulla haereſis damnata ſit, &amp;c.</hi> as if no hereſie were condemned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Councell.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:12177:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:12177:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="reason">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:12177:27"/>
            <head>The fourth reaſon of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular hereſies.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the recitall of particular hereſies, conſidering that I aime at no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g diſcourſe in this my treatiſe, I will beginne briefly with <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagianiſme</hi> making this ſillogiſme: they which hold the ſame opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Pelagius and vſe the ſame argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts that Pelagius did, are Pelagians, but the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts hold with Pelagius and vſe his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: <hi>Ergo,</hi> they are Pelagians. The aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I prooue out of Hieroms workes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Pelagians, who hold (as he teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>ad Cteſiphontem,</hi>) that <hi>Mandata dei are poſsibilia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hierom. lib. <hi>2</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gods commandements are poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be kept:</hi> and prooue the ſame by our ſauiour his ſaying: <hi>Iugum meum ſuaue eſt: my yoke is eaſie, &amp; mandata eius non ſunt grauia, and his commaundements are not grieuous:</hi> to which the learned father anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, <hi>Levia ſunt ad comparationem Iudaicae
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12177:27"/> ſuperſtitionis, they are light in reſpest of the Iewes ſuperſtion.</hi> Secondly they thus diſpute, <hi>Si in operibus meis deus mihi adiutor extite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, non mihi debetur merces ſedei qui in me operatus est: if my good things come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god, then there is no revvard for me &amp;c.</hi> To which he anſwereth thus: <hi>Contra Deum ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma linguam tuam: arme thy tongue againſt God, and ſo forth:</hi> are not theſe the very ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of Papiſts? Reade the Rhemiſtes vpon the places remembred, alſo vpon the ſecond of the Corinth. 5. cap. 10. where thou ſhalt finde this blaſphemy, <hi>that heauen is as vvell the reward of good workes, as hell is the stipend of evill workes:</hi> which is the drift of the argument of the Pelagians. I will adioyne ſome other ſayings of the ſame Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by which euery one may further ſee the truth of this my charge. <hi>Facilia dicis dei mandata &amp; tamen nullum proferre potes qui vniuerſa compleverit: thou affirmeſt the commandements are eaſie, and yet thou canſt not bring forth any that hath kept them.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Tunc iuſti ſumus quando nos peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res fatemur: &amp; iuſtitia nostra a non ex proprie
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12177:28"/> conſtat merito ſed ex dei miſericordia, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cente ſcriptura Iuſtus eſt accuſator ſui, in principio ſermonis. Then are we righteous when we confeſſe our ſelues ſinners, and our righteouſneſſe conſiſteth not of our merits, but of gods mercie, ſeing the ſcripture ſaith: The righteous is the accuſer of himſelfe.</hi> To let paſſe the reſt of his moſt excellent ſayings I come to the hereſie of Montaniſts.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>2.</hi> haereſie of Montaniſme.</head>
               <p>The Church in Tertullians time taught, that faſting was reſtrained neither to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine daies, nor to certaine meates: which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion Tertullian beeing a Montaniſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futeth in his booke <hi>aduerſus Pſeuchicos.</hi> That the Church ſo taught I prooue out of his ſecond chapter, where he ſetteth downe the arguments vſed againſt Montanus and confuteth them: The Church is brought in ſpeaking thus: <hi>Indifferenter ieiunandum ex arbttrio, pro temporibus &amp; cauſis vniuſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſque, ſic &amp; Apoſtolos dicunt obſeruaſſe nullum aliud imponentes iugum certorum &amp; in commune omnibus obeundorum ieiunio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. We muſt faſt as the cauſe of euery one
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12177:28"/> requireth, and the Apoſtles did thus obſerue it, laying no yoke of certaine and determined faſts vpon men.</hi> You ſee how the Church plainely ſpeaketh againſt the reſtraining of faſting to certaine daies, and as plaine is her ſpeech immediatly after againſt the reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to certaine meates. <hi>Xerophagius verò novum affectati officii nomen &amp; proximum Ethnicae ſuperſtitioni. The eating of certain drie meates is a newe name of straunge and affected office neere to the ſuperſtition of the Heathen.</hi> Againe, <hi>Apostolus est detestator e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum, qui ſicut nubere prohibent, ita iubent cibis abſtinere à deo conditis. The Apoſtle himſelfe deteſteth them that forbid to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and commaund to abstaine from meates created of God.</hi> The verdict the Church gaue concerning faſting which in that book Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian as a Montaniſt would confute: out of which teſtimonies I thus conclude. They which reſtraine faſting to certaine meates and times, holde not as the auncient Church helde, but with Montanus: the Papiſtes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine faſting to certen meates &amp; to certen times: <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Papiſts hold not with the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12177:29"/> auncient church, but with the Montaniſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſame, and as they doe hold with them concerning faſting ſo doe they like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the marriage of Miniſters, as may be prooued out of his booke <hi>Monogany,</hi> &amp; 12. chap. which he wrote beeing a Montaniſt: the Miniſters were as he ſpeaketh <hi>digami, twiſe married: omnia licent epiſcopis,</hi> all things are lawefull for biſtops, which he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futeth by the text of the 1. of Timothy: and 3. chap. <hi>A biſhop must be the huſband of one wife,</hi> ſo that I may ſay in theſe two points <hi>Non ovum ovo ſimilius, quam Papiſtae Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanistis: the Papists and Montaniſts are both alike.</hi> And ſo I paſſe to the third haereſie of Cainiſme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>3</hi> haereſie of Cainiſme.</head>
               <p>The haereſie which teacheth that he which before baptiſme had a wife and ſhee dying, the partie marrying another, ought not to be conſecrated biſhoppe, is by S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom in his Epiſtle to Oceanus called <hi>Cania Haereſes,</hi> The haereſie of Caine: In which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle he anſwereth the place of the 1. of Tim 3. cap. <hi>That a Biſhop must be the husband of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12177:29"/> one vvife,</hi> ſaying, <hi>praecipit ne ſacerdotes bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na aut trina coniugia ſortiantur more Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeorum aut Patriarcharum,</hi> He commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that prieſts haue not two or 3 wiues, after the manner of the Iewes and Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches. Now who is ſo ignorant that kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth not the Papiſts to hold this haereſie of Caine, and to abuſe the place of Timothy to that purpoſe: <hi>hanc haereſim ſequitur Romana Eccleſia,</hi> ſaith Eraſmus, this haereſie is embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the Romiſh Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>4.</hi> hereſie of Manicheiſme</head>
               <p>Although I might be very long in this haereſie, ſhewing where in the Papiſts agree with the Manichees: yet I will reduce their agreement to three heads: firſt the Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chees hold the ſcriptures to be corrupt, <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Morib. cap.</hi> 29. which opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he confuteth in theſe wordes: <hi>ſi Pauli epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolam ad Romanos ſcriptam corruptam eſſe contendis aliam proferas incorruptam, vel alium codicem potius in quo eiuſdem epiſtola eadem ſyncera &amp; incorrupta eſt,</hi> if for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thou contendeſt, that S. Paules epiſtle to the Romans is corrupt; thou muſt ſhewe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12177:30"/> incorrupt, or rather another book of the ſame Apoſtle wherein the ſame epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle is ſyncere &amp; vncorrupt. <hi>Canus Lindanus &amp; Reinolds</hi> for my owne part I thinke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing inferiour to theſe Haereticks in this point, nay haue not the Papiſts corrupted this ſame Epiſtle? leauing out the 11. cap. 6. v. all this ſentence, <hi>but if it be of workes it is no more of grace, or els workes were no more workes.</hi> For it cleane ouerthroweth their grand Haereſie: here for the ſame accuſation of diuine ſcripture I charge them with <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidianiſme,</hi> for <hi>Helvius</hi> held the ſame, as Hierome witneſſeth in his booke againſt him: <hi>tibi ſtultiſsime perſvaſiſti graeocs codi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces eſſe falſatos:</hi> O foole in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree thou haſt perſwaded thy ſelfe that the greeke coppies are falſified. And againe, <hi>Tu mira impude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia haec in graecis codicibus fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſata eſſe dicis</hi> thou with wonderfull impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie ſayeſt theſe things are falſified in the greeke bookes. Thus the Papiſts ioyne with Helvidius, and therefore by Hierome his verdict as they are full fooles, ſo haue they braſen faces. Secondly they permitted their
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12177:30"/> hearers to marrie, but not their elect as they called them: <hi>August. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Mor. Mani. cap.</hi> 19. <hi>Auditores veſtri quorum apud vos ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus est gradus ducere atque habere vxores non prohibentur: your hearers which are in the</hi> 2 <hi>degree are not forbidden to marrie:</hi> out of which place I gather that they did not condemne marriages ſimply, as the Papiſtes would make them, &amp; if they did can any one ſpeake more contemptuouſly of mariage then the Papiſtes doe.</p>
               <p>M. Martin in his diſcouery,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 15. <hi>ſect.</hi> 11.</note> calleth it a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning of ſacred orders. Innocentius &amp; Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricius diſprooue it by theſe 2. places: <hi>be yee holy becauſe I am holy:</hi> and againe: <hi>they that are in the fleſh cannot pleaſe God:</hi> and theſe arguments are ſtill maintained by the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neddeſt Papiſtes, by which they conclude that mariage is an enemie to holines, and a friend to filthines: the Lord rebuke them for theſe their blaſphemies,</p>
               <p>Thirdly in faſting they are right Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chees, for as Auguſtine ſaith <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. they did <hi>nihil carnium guſtare,</hi> and yet did eate <hi>exquiſitas &amp; peregrinas fruges multis fercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12177:31"/> varietas,</hi> they did eate no fleſh, &amp; yet did eate many and ſtrange fruites varied in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſhes: yea (as Auguſtine ſaieth) if one of their elect ſhould but annoint his lippes with bacon, or but take the ſauour of it, as a brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of his faſt, or abſtinence, he ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to hell fire; is not this the right po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh faſt? therefore I ſay to the Papiſtes as he did to theſe heretikes: <hi>quaeſo aduertite erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res:</hi> I deſire you conſider your errors.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>5.</hi> hereſie of Colliridianiſme.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> &amp; hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. <hi>79.</hi>
                  </note>The Collyridians as Epiphanius writeth worſhipped the virgin Mary: againſt whom he writeth thus: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, let no man worſhip Marie, the word vſed ſignifieth to caſt himſelfe downe, and ſo to worſhip with religious Honour. To proue that the Papiſts worſhip Marie not with <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, <hi>ſeruice,</hi> which they graunt, but with <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, <hi>religious ſeruice,</hi> which they denie, I vſe their owne teſtimony vpon the 2. of Luke, and 39. verſe, where Anna is ſaide to worſhipp the Lord by faſting and prayers: their note is this, that faſting is an act of Religion, whereby we doe worſhip God
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12177:31"/> as we do by praier, then by their owne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine they worſhip Marie with <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious vvorſhip;</hi> for they faſt and pray to her. Their owne words are theſe in their Pſalter, made for the praiſe of Marie according to the Romanes manner. <hi>In omni tribulatione &amp; angustia ſuccurrat nobis Maria:</hi> in all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction let Marie help vs: And againe, <hi>Solue vincula reis, perfer lumen caecis, mala noſtra pelle, bona cuncta poſce, monſtra te eſſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem:</hi> that is, Looſe the bondes of priſoners, giue light to the blinde, driue away all our euills, obtaine al good things for vs, ſhew thy ſelfe to be a mother. Laſtly, <hi>Per virginem Mariam conſedat nobis Dominus ſalutem:</hi> that is, the Lord ſaue vs for the virgine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie her ſake: what greater things can they deſire at Gods hands? Nay, what chriſtian heart can abide theſe blaſphemies? if this be not to honour Marie, what is to honour her? I ende this hereſie with Epiphanius his queſtion, <hi>Quae Scriptura aliquid de hac re narrauit?</hi> what Scripture ſpeaketh thus?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>6.</hi> hereſie of Angeliſme.</head>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:12177:32"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iraeneus lib. <hi>1</hi>
                  </note>In regard of breuitie I will knitt vp many hereſies together: the Carpocratians wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the Images of Ieſus; the Valentini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans the croſſe: the Heracleonites prayed for the dead.<note place="margin">Epiphan. <hi>14.</hi> Haereſ.</note> Elxay the horrible heretike taught praier in an vnknowen tongue. <hi>Nemo quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat interpretationem, ſed ſolum in oratione haec dicat: Let no man ſeeke for interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but onely let him pray thus.</hi> I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this ſixth particular hereſie brieflie ſpeak of Angeliſme:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Haereſ.</hi> 39.</note> 
                  <hi>Angelici</hi> (ſaieth Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine) <hi>in angelorum cultu ſunt inclinati: the Angelists were inclined to the worſhipping of Angels.</hi> Iraeneus likewiſe ſheweth the practiſe of the church againſt this worſhip.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 59.</note> 
                  <hi>Eecleſia non facit aliquid inuocationibus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicis ſed mundè &amp; purè dirigit orationes ad Dominum qui omnia fecit: The Church doth not any thing by prayer to Angels, but purely directeth her praier to the Lord that made all things.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. de vero dei ſimul. cap. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> Againe Lactantius writeth thus. <hi>Non eſt in Angelis quicquam niſi pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendi neceſsitas, itaque nullum ſibi honorem tribui volunt, quorum honor in deo eſt. There
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12177:32"/> is nothing in the Angels but neceſsitie to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, therefore they will haue no honour to be giuen to them vvhoſe honour is in God.</hi> And in his firſt booke and ſeuenth chapter? <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistri Dei coli non volunt, quippe qui nihil praeter iuſſum, &amp; Dei voluntatem faciunt.</hi> Gods attendants will not be adored, for they doe nothing but his commaundement and will. If theſe men were aliue, what would they haue written againſt the Papiſtes who maintaine the adoration and worſhipping of Angels?</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="reason">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:12177:33"/>
            <head>The fifth reaſon of the popiſh diſsolute and diſcomfortable doctrine.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not vnknowne how the Papiſts without all ſhame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe our doctrine of looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, wheras all our writings, ſermons, and exerciſes tende to holines of life: for we preach mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the fleſh, continuance in prayer, and in a word all holy duties: we permit no filthie ſtewes, neither by raſh vowes cauſe inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie and fornication, which are notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and knowne things amongſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts <hi>Vrbs est</hi> (ſaith Mantuan) <hi>iam tota lupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar, the whole citie is a ſtewes,</hi> ſpeaking of Rome. And as the liues of the Papiſts haue beene odious to God, and to man, ſo I doubt not but in this motiue to prooue that their doctrine tendeth to horrible diſſolutenes, and helliſh horrour. In Aquinas his ſupple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>art.</hi> 2. <hi>quaest.</hi> 2. it is taught that no man
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12177:33"/> ought to be contrite in heart for originall ſinne, which is a licentious and carnall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: did not the prophet Dauid in the 51. pſalme, confeſſe <hi>that in ſinne his mother con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued him:</hi> and S. Paul crieth out,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> 
               <hi>O miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man that I am, who ſhall redeeme me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this bodie of ſinne?</hi> out of which places we may gather the griefe that thoſe holy men of God conceiued for their naturall corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Papiſts reaſon why we muſt not be contrite for originall ſinne, is worthie of conſideration. <hi>Non eſt voluntarium: it is not voluntarie,</hi> ſay they. The ſyllogiſme is thus to be made: We are not to be contrite but for voluntarie ſinnes: but originall ſinne is not voluntarie: <hi>ergo</hi> we are not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite for it. I anſwer to the propoſition, they might as well conclude that it is no ſinne: let Auguſtine diſſolue this knotte, who in his 1. booke of Retract. and 13. chap. writeth thus: <hi>Nullo modo peccatum est niſi ſit volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarium, peccatum quippe illudintelligendum est quod tantummodo peccatum est, non poena peccati, quamvis &amp; illa, quae immeritò non voluntaria peccata dicuntur, quia vel à neſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientibus
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12177:34"/> vel à coactis perpetrantur non om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninò poſſunt ſine voluntate committi, quoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am &amp; ille qui peccat ignorans, voluntarie quoque peccat, &amp;c. It is no ſinne except it be voluntarie, this ſpeach is to be vnderstood of ſinne which is ſimply ſinne, and not a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſinne, although thoſe ſinnes which are vnfitly called ſinnes against our wills (becauſe they are ether committed by conſtraint, or by ignorance) cannot be altogether without the conſent of will, for he which ſinneth of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, ſinneth willingly.</hi> Thus hath Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine anſweared the popiſh reaſon to the full.</p>
            <p>Secondly the Papiſts teach, that ſome ſinnes are veniall of their owne nature, that is deſerue not eternall death, which muſt needes cauſe men to caſt off the bridle and reynes of holy life: why doeth Baſil in his ſhorter Definitions and 10. rule, prooue that euery ſinne is deadly by this place, <hi>The vva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of ſinne is death.</hi> But to withdraw men from the opinion of the lightnes of ſinne, well ſaith Hierome <hi>ad Caelantiam: Tanto facilius abstinemus à quocun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> delicto, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tò
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12177:34"/> illud magis metuimus, nec etiam titò ad maior a progreditur, qui etiam parva formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat. We abstaine ſo much the more eaſily fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne, by how much we feare the ſame: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he make hast to greater ſinnes which feareth the leſſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly the Papiſts teach, that the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment giues grace <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> of worke wrought without faith: for howſoeuer Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine requireth it as a diſpoſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion, yet the Cenſure of Colo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which knew the Romiſh doctrine as well as Bellarmine reaſoneth thus: <hi>pueris extra omnem dubitationis ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſacramenta prodeſſe nemo ſanae mentis dubitare potest, in quibus tamen nulla est fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, nulla cordis motio, nullus peccatorum do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, aut gemitus, &amp; ſanè ſi in pueris eaſit Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentorum natura, cur non erit ſimilis omnino in alijs maximè? eùm neque Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus, nec Eccleſia vnquam vel vllam diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis fecit mentionem. Without all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie children receiue benefit by the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in whome there is no faith, no motion of the heart, no ſorrow for ſinne, and why doe not others likewiſe ſo? ſeeing neither Christ
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12177:35"/> nor the Church mentioneth any reaſon to the contrarie.</hi> What is this, but to cauſe men to come without repentance to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments? for if thou be not a murderer, a theefe, or an adulterer, &amp;c. the ſacraments will repleniſh thee with grace: but (Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Reader) take heede of this diſſolute and looſe doctrine, for he deſtroieth himſelfe, and damneth his ſoule, that commeth to the Sacraments without faith and repentance, and he is ſo farre from receiuing grace, that he purchaſeth Gods eternall wrath and ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſpleaſure to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly the Papiſts bind their votaries, prelats and prieſts to keepe their vowes, which yet burne in filthie luſts, yea are not thoſe vowes vngodly which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be kept without inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinency?<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.11.</note> If widows (as S. Paule ſaith) waxe wanton againſt Chriſt beeing warme, idle, and well fedde, and ſo luſt after husbands, what doe many papiſts more warme, more idle, and better fed then thoſe poore widows were, that S. Paule ſpeaketh of? What doe they I ſay luſt after? but with them this diuinitie is currant, <hi>ſi non caſtè,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12177:35"/> cautè tamen:</hi> if not chaſtly, yet warily.</p>
            <p>Fiftly the papiſts teach that the pope may giue pardon <hi>de paenitentijs iniungendis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fulk aganſt Allen.</note> that is, <hi>of penance to be performed, Ergo</hi> a man may haue a pardon before he ſinne, which is to open a gappe to all ſinne, yea the rich man may boldly tranſgreſſe, becauſe he is able to giue largely for pardons.</p>
            <p>Sixtly,<note place="margin">Ferus vpon Matth. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futeth it. <hi>Aquin.</hi> 22.25. <hi>q.</hi> 9. <hi>ar.</hi>
               </note> they teach that the loue of a mans e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie is counſelled by our ſauiour Chriſt, not commaunded, ſo that a man is not bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to loue his enemie by Gods commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, O carnal &amp; lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tious libertines, what is more eaſie for man then to loue his friende? what is more againſt the proud ſpirit of a man the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to loue his enemie? And ſo from diſſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of doctrine I come to the diſcomfort of the ſame.</p>
            <p>No man ought to be aſſured of his ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by faith,<note place="margin">Cenſ. col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but by hope (ſaith the papiſt) reſting vpon his owne merits, which is to racke and torment a chriſtian ſoule, for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on muſt ſay with Hierom in his dialogue againſt the Luciferans, <hi>Credo Domine &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſecundum fidem mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fieri nolo, ſic enim
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12177:36"/> peribo:</hi> I beleeue Lord, yet let it not be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my beleeue, for then I periſh: and with Auguſtine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>10.</hi> lib. con. &amp; <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>tota ſpes mea non niſi in valde magna miſericordia tua:</hi> my whole hope is only in thy great mercy: but more of this in another motiue, and therefore I oppoſe their own Catechiſme againſt them which excellently confuteth this deſperate doctrine:<note place="margin">Cat. col.</note> 
               <hi>profecto nequè in aignitatem fidei, ne que operum meorum, vt me certum facia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rectè reſpexero.</hi> Verely for certainty that god is mercifull to me I muſt neither looke to the dignitie of my faith or of my works, <hi>ſed in paſsionem tuam ô Christe oculos men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis defigam,</hi> but O Chriſt I will faſten the eyes of my minde vpon thy paſsion, <hi>cum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecerit virtus mea non diffidam, quia ſi ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis tuus interpellet pro me ſalvus ero,</hi> when my goodnes is eclipſed I will not diſtruſt, for if thy bloode entreat for me I ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
            <p>Secondly they teach that by contrition &amp; ſorrow for ſinne,<note place="margin">Stapl. A. quae. <hi>7.</hi> ar. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> the guilt of ſinne is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken away, but becauſe a man can not be aſſured of the ſufficiencie of his ſorow, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>efore
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:12177:36"/> he muſt both confeſſe and ſatisfie Gods iuſtice for his ſinnes: O helliſh deuice of man! If no man can be aſſured of the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie of his contrition and ſorrow, how can he certifie his ſoule that his Confeſsion and Satisfaction are ſufficient? if he can not be aſſured of one, he cannot likewiſe be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the other, and ſo muſt needes be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp in the gulfe of deſpaire. Hold this therefore (Chriſtian ſoule) that thy reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation dependeth not vpon ſufficient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, contrition, and ſatisfaction, but vpon the merit of Chriſt; and ſay as the gloſſe doth vpon <hi>Gratian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 376.</note> that theſe doe not cauſe and deſerue forgiuenes of ſinnes, but onely Gods mercie is the cauſe thereof; and that true ſorrow is a ſigne to thee of the forgiuenes of thy ſinnes. And as the doctrine of Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is deſperate, ſo it is a moſt looſe and diſſolute doctrine: for,
<q>Si dederis marcas, &amp; eis impleveris areas,</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Culpâ ſolvêris quacun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ligatus eris:</hi> that is, <hi>If thou fillest the Popes coffers with mony, thou ſhalt be looſed from all thy faults.</hi> Alas, alas, what will not a man giue for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12177:37"/> of his ſoule?<note place="margin">Iob 2. Mich. 6.</note> thouſands of riuers oyle; yea he had rather cauſe his ſonnes to paſſe through fire then to performe true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="reason">
            <head>The ſixt reaſon of Idolatrie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N Philoſophie there was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt no opinion ſo voide of reaſon, but it found ſome pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, and as it was in philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, ſo now it is in Diuinity; for elſe how could the Papiſts defende the worſhip of images? Of theſe popiſh idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters I ſay with Lactantius,<note place="margin">Lib. de orig. erroris. cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Venia concedi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test imperitis &amp; ijs qui ſe ſapientes non fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentur, his vero non poteſt qui ſapientiam profeſsi ſtultitiam potius exhibent. The ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant may be pardoned, but to thoſe that profeſsing wiſdome manifest their follie, pardon cannot be granted.</hi> But let vs ſee how they excuſe their idolatrie.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:12177:37"/>
            <p>Firſt Bellarmine maketh a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene an idol and an image:<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>5</hi> de Imag.</note> an idol is an i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of that which is not, but an image is a figure of that which is: to take his graunt I will firſt conclude out of his owne wordes that the Papiſts are idolaters, and then by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible arguments diſprooue this diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. They which worſhip images of thoſe things that are not extant, are idolaters: but the Papiſts worſhippe the images of thoſe things that are not extant:<note place="margin">Heerbrant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. com.</note> 
               <hi>ergo</hi> they are ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters. The aſſumption I thus prooue: Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher, George, and Katherine were neuer extant, but they worſhip their images: <hi>ergo</hi> they worſhip images of thinges that neuer were. For the diſproofe of his diſtinction I will vſe his owne arguments, and confeſsion againſt himſelfe. <hi>First</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture neuer calleth any true image an idoll,</hi> this I diſprooue out of his 13. chap. where he confeſſeth that the Iewes worſhipped God in an image or idol. That in which the Iewes worſhipped God, is an idol: but the Iewes worſhipped God in an image: <hi>ergo</hi> an idol is an image. Secondly (ſaith he)
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12177:38"/> the ſcripture calleth Idolls <hi>elilim,</hi> that is <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> and vſeth other names to the ſame purpoſe. If this reaſon be good, then becauſe the ſcripture calleth Idols <hi>peſilim,</hi> &amp; by other like names, it muſt of neceſsitie follow that they repreſent ſomething: if any demaund, why the ſcripture calleth Idols nothing, and vanitie, and lies, I anſwere becauſe of their effects, ſo ſaith Kimhi: <hi>dabar ſhe eno mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnil</hi> that which profiteth not, is called <hi>elil,</hi> for in truth they neither helpe the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of them, nor can they helpe them, and ſo are meere vanity: and by this reaſon is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered his argument taken out of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians 8 chap. where an Idol is called no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, nothing it is in regard of profitte and commodity, yet may it repreſent ſomthing: His fourth reaſon is, becauſe the Fathers cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Hereſies Idols: as an haereſie is a falſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination, ſo [ſaith he] is an Idoll a falſe Image: thus indeede the fathers ſpeake, out of which I thus diſpute.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hierom.</hi> Hoſea 4.</note> An hereſie is an falſe opinion, and imagination of ſome thing whereof there is a trueth,<note place="margin">Epiph. Haer. <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> as for example, the <hi>Anthropo morphits</hi> that thought god was in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12177:38"/> ſhape &amp; proportion like a man, did they not conceaue a falſe imagination of a reall thing whereof there is a trueth, <hi>Ergo,</hi> by the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites owne argument an Idol may repreſent a thing, that hath a beeing and ſubſiſtance: but there is a plaine and euident demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion why the Fathers call haereſies Idols, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe to ſerue God as we liſt, and not as he will is Idolatrie: he neither taketh nor requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth any thing at our hands, beſides his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and that according to his will, <hi>who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth this at your handes,</hi> (ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Eſay:) vnleſſe therfore they can prooue that God will be ſerued with materiall and artificiall Images, and is content to accept that honour as done to himſelfe, that is yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto them, their adoring them maketh them idols, and themſelues Idolaters. His laſt reaſon taken out of Tertullian cleane ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth his cauſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſaith Tertullian) <hi>graecè formam ſonat, ab eo per diminutionem</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>aequè apud nos formulam fecit, igitur omnis forma vel formula idolum ſe dici ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſcit.</hi> This word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in greeke ſignifieth a ſhape, whence <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is deriued as a dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutiue,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12177:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:12177:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:12177:40"/> and with vs ſignifieth any ſhape, &amp; therefore euery ſhape or likeneſſe may be called an idol. If euery ſhape may be called an idol, then a ſhape of a thing that is exta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t may be ſo called: but by Tertullians opinion eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhape may be ſo called, <hi>Ergo</hi> a ſhape of a thing that is extant and hath a ſubſiſtance: now whereas the Ieſuite in fine and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion out of Euſtathius ſaith that an Idol <hi>is inane ſpectrum, &amp; phantaſma,</hi> a vaine fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ſuch as we frame in our imaginations, &amp; as the ſhaddowes &amp; ghoſtes of the dead are, doth it not as well prooue that for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is nothing, as it doth that it repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth nothin? yes verely, for in trueth thoſe things are as he ſpeaketh <hi>vmbrae,</hi> ſhadows, &amp; <hi>cavae imagines,</hi> images without any ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, ſo that he might by this argue an Idol to haue no matter, &amp; no bodily ſubſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as he doth that it is nothing formally, that is re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſenteth nothing. Hauing retorted his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments againſt himſelfe, I wil now briefly ſhew that an Idol repreſenteth ſomething. The 2. Commandement ſhall helpe vs with the firſt argument, in which, as the Papiſts
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:12177:40"/> confeſſe an Idol is forbidden, but that which is there forbidden, is a ſimilitude of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as of things in heauen and in earth,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.15.16.</note> or vnder the earth, ſo ſaith Moſes, <hi>thou ſhalt not make the forme of a man, or of a woman, or of any creature in the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly I diſprooue their diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the 14. of wiſdome, verſe, 1. where <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the beginning of whordome is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the inventio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Idols, what doth he call an Idol? read the 15 verſe and thou ſhalt find that the father ſorrowing for his ſonne, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, worketh his Image, and ſo worſhippeth the dead as God: by which euery man may ſee that an Idol &amp; an Image are there put to ſignifie both one thing, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he will hold that the Image which the father maketh of his ſonne repreſenteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: which no Papiſt though exceeding bolde and blinde dare affirme.</p>
            <p>Thirdly I demaund whether the Images which Carpocrats worſhipped were not I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols? if only idols be forbidden in the 2.<note place="margin">Jraen. lib. <hi>1</hi> cap. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> com. the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Images there forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt be idols, yet were they Images of Ieſus. I let paſſe the images of Paule,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiph.</hi> 24.</note> Pythagoras and others
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12177:41"/> which euery one know to repreſent ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. The Melchizedechians alſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the Image of Moſes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiph.</hi> 55.</note> yet can no man deny that to be an Idoll, out of all which it is eaſie to conclude, that an Idoll is not alwaies an image of that which is not.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Baal himſelfe, which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deteſteth as a moſt infamous Idoll was nothing elſe but a corporall Image erected vnto God, by which the people dreamed they ſerued and pleaſed God, as may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by Hoſea in his 2. chapter: <hi>At that day ſaith the Lord, thou ſhalt call me no more Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al:</hi> And in Elias time, 1. King. 18, the Iſraelites haulted betweene two opinions, partly ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God, partly their Idolls; likewiſe the Gentiles which the king of Aſſyria placed in Samaria (2. King. 17.33) feared God &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped their Idolls. Laſtly the Iewes ſware by God &amp; their King,<note place="margin">Sophon. 1.</note> that is, by their Idolls, for they called their Idolls Kings, ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it as if it were a proper name, they ſware by God and by Malchon, but that can not be, becauſe of the affixe and pronoune that is ioyned with it, for proper names are
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:12177:41"/> not compou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded with affixes &amp; pronounes, as Elias proueth; by all which teſtimonies it is euident and plaine, that all the Iewes were not ſo ſeduced as to thinke their Idolls to be God, for then they would not haue bin like a cake halfe baked,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap</hi> 7.4. <hi>ver.</hi>
               </note> (as the Prophet Hoſea ſpeaketh) now ſeruing God and then their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolls.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, the Heathen did not thinke their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolls to be God, which I prooue out of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantius:<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> de ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro dei ſim.</note> 
               <hi>Non ipſa inquiunt timemus ſedeos adquorum imaginem ficta, &amp; quorum nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus conſecrata ſunt: Wee doe not reuerence and vvorſhip the Idolls themſelues, but thoſe which are repreſented by them, and thoſe to vvhome they are conſecrated:</hi> what is more direct then this againſt Bellarmine, who would haue men beleeue that the Heathen did account their Idolls to be God, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reuileth M. Caluin a man of famous memorie not being able with any probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to take away his arguments. And if that opinion of Macrobius be true, that all the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods are to be referred to the ſunne,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Satur. ca</hi> 7.</note> as Apollo, Capis, Serapis and others, how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:12177:42"/> it enter into the heart of any learned man to imagine, that the Gentiles were ſo ignorant as to think their idols to be God, except they could not diſtinguiſh betweene them and the Sunne: their idols then repreſenting the Sunne, of neceſsitie it followeth, that they repreſented ſomething; except the Sunne be nothing. Thus the Papiſts defending Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, goe about to take the Sunne out of the world, making it nothing, and ſo prooue themſelues vnworthie the light therof. And ſo hauing diſprooued his diſtinction, I will proceede to other of his aſſertions, and then ſet downe Lactantius his reaſons againſt I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, which are as directly oppoſite to the Papiſts, as if he had of purpoſe written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. Bellarmine confeſſeth that in his 8. chap. that <hi>Idiotae qui vident picturas, &amp; non poſſunt legere ſcripturas, poſſunt ac de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent à praelatis &amp; Concionatoribus inſtitui, alioquin fateor non ſine periculo exhiberi imperitis eiuſmodi picturas. The lay people vvhich ſee and beholde Images and can not reade Scriptures, ought to be instructed of their prelates and preachers, elſe I confeſſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:12177:42"/> that Images to the ignorant are not vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out daunger deliuered.</hi> This is as much as to giue a madde man a ſworde, and then to watch ouer him leaſt he hurt himſelfe: but haue the Papiſts preachers to teach the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? yea, their prieſts for ignorance are very Idols, many yeares agoe was this complaint vttered that in times paſt there were golden prieſtes and treene cuppes,<note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but now golden cuppes and treene prieſts, but of this ſee more in a former motiue: and whereas he ſaith that lay people may reade the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, doth he not bidde defiance to other Papiſts,<note place="margin">Cenſ. Col.</note> who by might and maine maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that the Scriptures are not to be reade of the ignorant. But nowe let vs ſee what the people are to be taught,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar.</hi> 20.</note> they are to be taught, that Images are to be worſhipped by themſelues not accidentally or impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, ſo that worſhippe is due to images themſelues, and not onely as they repreſent ſome other thing: are the people able to reach this diuinitie? nay the very Papiſts themſelues cannot poſsibly conceiue theſe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:12177:43"/> diſtinctions, yea they are flatly oppoſite to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther learned papiſts: and laſtly the Heathen neuer taught ſo grosſly of the worſhipping of their Images. To goe a little further, the people muſt not be taught that Images are to be worſhipped with the higheſt kind of worſhippe which is due to god,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>cap.</hi> 22. &amp; 23</note> as touching their manner of ſpeech and wordes, but, <hi>ſi de re ipſa agatur imagines impropriè coluntur eo genere cultus quo examplar ipſum, if it be concerning the matter and thing it ſelfe an Image accidentally muſt be honoured with the ſame honour wherewith the thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented is worſhipped and honoured.</hi> Is not this to ſpeake myſteries to the people,<note place="margin">Bell. cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> yea to ſpeake lies in hypocriſie? Alphonſus de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro a learned Papiſt accounteth Serenus Biſhop of Maſsilia, and Epiphanius enemies to Images, becauſe they brake them in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and yet wee may not doe ſo without haereſie (for ſaith Bellarmine) when Serenus brake them, the people: beeing neere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to the faith worſhipped the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for gods: it were hard for Bellarmine to prooue the trueth of this ſentence, namely a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:12177:43"/> to worſhip an image for God, but if Serenus did well for breaking them, becauſe the people worſhipped them as Gods, why may not we break them without any hurt, for it is well knowne that the ignorant pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts amongſt vs haue taken them for gods? Thus hauing gathered out of Bellarmine his garden ſome ſweete flowers and noſegaies, nay rather poyſonful hearbs, I come now to Lacta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius his reaſons againſt images, which whether they conclude not againſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts as well as againſt the Heathen, let any indifferent man iudge. <hi>Postquam Deus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sto eſſe caepit</hi> (ſaith Lactantius) <hi>iam ſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eius non est opus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap.</note> 
               <hi>ſupervacua enim est hominis imago, cùm homo praeſto est. When God is preſent there is no neede of his image, for the image of man is ſuperfluous vvhen man himſelfe is preſent.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</note> Yet Bellarmine will needes defende the image of God, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he be preſent euery where, becauſe he is not ſeene, and ſo cutteth the ſinewes of Lactantius his reaſon: and here I would haue the Reader to note that Bellarmine prooueth that images of God may be made,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:12177:44"/> and as he prooueth the ſame, ſo it is their practiſe to paint the Father like an old man, becauſe he ſo appeared to Daniel, yet it is not certen (ſaith he) in the church whether ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are to be made or no, out of which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion I conclude, that he teacheth vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine doctrine, yea that their Church pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſeth thoſe things which they are not ſure of, and therefore dealeth Antichriſtianly with the people. But I would know of Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine, why the Father may be painted like an old man, and the holy ghoſt like a Doue, ſeeing he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demneth the image of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie painted in forme of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hauing three faces, theſe images (ſaith he) are monſters, and are not the other ſo? if you diſprooue this, then yee likewiſe diſprooue the other: for the painters may as well defende the one as the other. To returne to Lactantius in the ſame chap. and booke, he thus writeth, <hi>Dei in aeternum viventis vivum &amp; ſenſibile debet eſſe ſimulachrum, it aque ſimulachrum Dei non est quod digitis hominum fabrica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. God which liueth for euer ought to haue a liuing and ſenſible Image, therefore it is
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:12177:44"/> not Gods image vvhich is made with mens ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds.</hi> Again, it images are to be worſhipped, then the makers of them are much more to be worſhipped.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Nam non potest eſſe quicqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> artifice matus. For ther can be nothing grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the workman, who is alwaies better then his worke:</hi> to which Bellarmine anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that images are to bee worſhipped not for themſelues, but for the things which they repreſent, as if the heathen might not haue ſaid as much and ſhaped the ſame aunſwer: yea he is not aſhamed to confeſſe and graunt that man may bee worſhipped, if he ment of ciuill worſhip wee would not contend, but ſeing he meaneth religious worſhip, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt his doctrine; for the reaſon being ſtrong againſt the heathen, it is as ſtrong againſt the papiſts: and therefore <hi>I</hi> thus conclude it, if i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages may bee worſhipped with religious worſhip: then may man who is a true image of God be ſo worſhipped; but man ought not ſo to be worſhipped: <hi>Ergo,</hi> neither ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. <hi>I</hi> will adioyne moe ſayings of Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Religio &amp; veneratio nulla alia tenenda eſt, niſi vnius Dei, no religion &amp; worſhip is to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12177:45"/> be embraced but of god only: Quidigitur opus eſt tantos ſumptus, vel finge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dis, vel cole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dis i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginibus impe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dere? What need the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is there to beſtow ſo much cost in making of Images, and worſhipping them?</hi> For, <hi>Nihil colendum eſt quod mortalibus oculis cernitur:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Nothing that is ſeene vvith the eyes of man is to bee worſhipped;</hi> and that the Papiſts may ſee how well the Gentiles and they agree, heare the Gentiles defence:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Non ipſatimemus ſedeos ad quorum imaginem ficta, &amp; quorum nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus conſecrata ſunt, cur igitur oculos ad coelum non tollitis? cur ad parietes ſpectatis? We do not adore the Images, but thoſe, whome they repreſent, and to whome they are dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and conſecrated, why then doe you not lift vp your eyes to heauen? and why doe you gaze vpon the walles:</hi> Out of this defence of the heathen (as I ſaid before) euery one may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that they did not defend their Idolls to be Gods, as Bellarmine would make them; yea we may learne that the Papiſts goe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then they did, for Bellarmine holdeth that the Images themſelues are to bee wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, and that they doe <hi>terminare vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem,</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:12177:45"/> worſhip goeth no further then the image not to the thing which is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the image: Thus I haue ſet downe Lactantius his arguments, which I deſire all Papiſtes to conſider without a preiudicate opinion for fauour of them: before I finiſh this reaſon I will ſet downe a ſyllogiſme or two, which I would haue them likewiſe to think vpon: Bellarmine confeſſeth that ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges may accidentally bee worſhipped with the ſame kinde of worſhip, that the things repreſented by them are to be worſhipped with: out of which <hi>I</hi> conclude that acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally there may bee many Gods; that which accidentally hath diuine worſhip, is acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally God, but images of God accidentally haue the ſame worſhip that God himſelfe hath: <hi>ergo</hi> they are accidentally Gods: and if this argument cannot moue them, yet let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſider that the man cannot bee excuſed from treaſon that giueth the proper titles of the kingdome to any vnder this pretence, that he doth it for honour of the King. The Lord (ſaieth Eſay) will not giue his glorie to another, and yet the papiſts ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 42.</note> he is content
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12177:46"/> that images by accident haue the ſame glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, yea why might not the Collyridian here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks by the ſame ſhift excuſe their idolatrie, and by as good reaſon offer cakes to the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine Marie as the papiſts doe candels to her: and howſoeuer Bellarmine minceth this point by this ſophiſticall diſtinction of acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall worſhip, yet doth their church wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the image of Chriſt and his croſſe with the ſame worſhip wherewith Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is worſhipped, ſo ſaith the fortreſſe of their faith, <hi>Crux Christi &amp; eius imago ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerari debet veneratione latriae, &amp; haec est opinio Thomae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>conſ.</hi> 4. <hi>art.</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>The croſſe &amp; image of Christ ought to be worſhipped with ſuch honour as is due to God, &amp; of this opinion is Thomas.</hi> Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coth indeed contradicted this opinion, but the church tooke part with Thomas againſt him, <hi>Communis opinio tenet oppoſitum, The common opinion holdeth the contrarie:</hi> And why doth their church ſing on this manner to the croſſe, <hi>O Crux ave ſpes vnita, auge piis iustitiam reiſque dona veniam: Haile croſſe our only hope, increaſe in the godly iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and giue thee guilty pardon:</hi> But to giue
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:12177:46"/> that honour which is due to Chriſt to the croſſe: For who is ſo ſimple as to reſt in Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmines anſwere that by <hi>Croſſe</hi> is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood Chriſt himſelfe, or els there is a rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall figure, called <hi>a faining of a perſon,</hi> this is but to faine an vntrueth: if their church were asked, eſpecially the vulgar people,<note place="margin">Vide Aqui. <hi>3.</hi> par. quae. <hi>25.</hi> art. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> they know no ſuch meaning. The ſecond ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme ſhalbe this, they which goe on pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to images, worſhip images the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues: but the papiſts go on pilgrimage to images: <hi>Ergo</hi> they worſhip the images themſelues: to this Bellarmine anſwereth, <hi>Peregrinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ad imagines rariores ſunt in Eccleſia, Pilgrimages to images are not often now v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the church,</hi> what they are now I will not diſpute, the litle freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting of pilgrimage cannot diſſolue the argument ſeing the thing is graunted. I leaue the practiſe of the Iewes who knew the meaning of Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, and yet [as Cornelius Tacitus wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth in his 5. booke of hiſtories.] <hi>Nulla ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulachra in templis ſunt: they haue no ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in their temples:</hi> Onely I wiſh the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to conſider that Epiphanius is reiected
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:12177:47"/> of Bellarmine, Auguſtine is aunſwered that he wrote againſt images when he was firſt conuerted, and yet he neuer retracted his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion: Two Councells of Conſtantinople, one of Franckfurte, and the fourth Councell of Eliberis muſt all giue place to the idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Councell of Neece: well may Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine by theſe aunſwers perſwade his beſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted diſciples to bee idolaters, but except hee hath better arguments and aunſwers euerie learned man will eaſilie eſpie his weake de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and in my iudgement it had bin better both for his credite &amp; conſcience that he had neuer defended the worſhipping of images, for I doubt not but by reading of him euery one not foreſtalled may be mooued to the truth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="reason">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:12177:47"/>
            <head>The ſeuenth reaſon of Blaſphemies.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving evicted the Papiſts to be guiltie of many grieuous crimes; as Haereſies, Idolatrie &amp;c I come now to Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies which are vttered by men of no ſmall account amongſt them: theſe blaſphemies without the reſt of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments here propounded, I doubt not but beeing throughly weighed by the reader, will leaue ſuch an impreſsion in him, that he ſhall haue iuſt cauſe to take part with God and Chriſt againſt the Pope who arroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to himſelfe a certaine Godhead. I begin firſt with Bellarmines blaſphemous argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>ſi nullo modo legem poſſemus ſeruare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2</hi> de Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Deus eſſet omni tyranno iniquior &amp; crudeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or: if we cannot poſsibly keepe the lawe of god, then God is more cruell, and vnrighteous the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any tyrant.</hi> What dogge would thus barke againſt god? for that no man can perfectly fulfill Gods commandements I ſhall prooue
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:12177:48"/> by ſuch arguments and teſtimonies as he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not accept againſt. To loue God with al our heart, with all our minde, ſoule, &amp; ſtrength, is <hi>angelica perfectio,</hi> an angelicall ſtate of life: but no man can come to angelicall perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: <hi>Ergo,</hi> no man can fullfill Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements. Secondly we are but <hi>viatores</hi> in this life, 1. trauellors, ſo that if we can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly fulfill all Gods commandements, there is no difference betwixt the life that we ſhall lead in our countrey, which is heauen, and this pilgrimage in which we nowe are, for beeing in heaven we can but loue God in that manner and meaſure which he requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. Well ſaith Nazianzen, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>not to ſinne is aboue the reach of man,</hi> and Bernard is directly appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to Bellarmine,<note place="margin">In his 50 ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon in can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti.</note> ſaying, <hi>Ergo mandando impoſsibilia, non praevaricatores homines fecit, ſed humiles, vt omne os obſtruatur &amp; accipientes quippe mandatum &amp; ſentientes aefectum clamabimus in caelum &amp; miſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur noſtri deus: God by commanding impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible things made not men tranſgreſſoures of his lawe, but humbleth them that euery
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:12177:48"/> mouth may be ſtopped, for receiuing a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, &amp; feeling our inability to keep it, we cry vnto God and he will haue mercie on vs.</hi> What is more plaine then this that god requireth impoſsible things at our ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds? To Bernard agreeth Auguſtine. <hi>In manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis est etiam quod iubemur or are remitte no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis debita noſtra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1</hi> Retr. cap. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>omnia ergo mandata ſacta deputantur quando quicquid non fit ignoſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. In Gods commandements we are bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to pray, forgiue vs our ſinnes, therefore all Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements are accepted as done, when that which is not done is pardoned.</hi> But why doe I heape vp teſtimonies of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? Let their maſter of Sentences him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſpeake,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> &amp;. diſt. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>cur praecipitur hominibus iſta perfectio? Why are me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commanded this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</hi> he anſwereth out of Auguſtine, <hi>quia non rectè curritur, ſiquo currendum eſt, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciatur: becauſe we cannot runne well except we knowe whether we muſt runne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. 2 <hi>q.</hi> 44. <hi>art</hi> 8.</note> So doth Aquinas vſe the very ſame anſwer by which it is apparent to all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that God commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth impoſsible things, and therefore by this blaſphemy muſt be more cruell then any ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:12177:49"/> but this might haue beene better borne withall, if they had vttered no moe blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous arguments. The Rhemiſts vpon the firſt of Timoth. chap. 4. wanting reaſons for their prohibition of meates and marriages, know not how to defend their practiſe but by an argument <hi>à pari,</hi> taken from equalitie: God in paradiſe did commaund abſtinence from one certaine tree, and alſo did forbidde in the time of the Law certaine degrees of marriage: <hi>ergo</hi> ſo may the Pope doe: O vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable, nay rather blaſphemous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents! if ye thus diſpute without all perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture in the ende ye ſhall haue the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. From Bellarmine and the Rhemiſts I come to their angelical Doctour, who in his ſupple. 25. <hi>quae. art.</hi> 1. concludeth thus: <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus potest, Ergo Paulus poteſt, Ergo papa po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test: Chriſt can doe it, therefore Paul can doe it, therefore the Pope can doe it.</hi> Make the ſyllogiſme and then the argument will be of greater force: whatſoeuer Chriſt can doe, that can Paul doe, and whatſoeuer Paul can doe, that can the Pope doe: but Chriſt can doe this: therefore Paul, and the Pope can
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:12177:49"/> doe it. But why are Paul and the pope ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together, ſeeing his authoritie is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from Peter? when Peters keies will not ſerue, then Pauls ſword muſt ſaue. To let paſſe theſe ſenſles diſputers, heare what is written in the firſt part of the 6. booke of Decretalls, and 6. title <hi>de electione,</hi> fol. 44. <hi>Papa non est homo, ſed vicarius Dei, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius acus, The pope is not a man, but Gods vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car, more expreſſely God.</hi> In the proheme of the Clementines and 3. folio, I finde the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the pope to be this: <hi>Papa, id eſt, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirabilis, nec deus es, nec homo, quaſineuter es inter vtrunque. The pope is called ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is wonderfull, thou art neither god nor man, but as it were a neuter betvvixt both.</hi> Againe in the Extravagants fol. 16. tit. 3. <hi>Suppoſit a plenitudine potestatis iuxta quam papae dici non potest, Domine, cur ita facis. Preſuppoſing the plenarie power by which no man may ſay to the pope, Maſter, why doeſt thou ſo,</hi> no not though (as it is in an other place) he leade innumerable ſoules with him by heapes to the deuill of hell. Nowe let Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normitan play his part, <hi>Papa &amp; Chriſtus fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:12177:50"/> vnum conſistorium.</hi> The pope and Chriſt make one conſiſtorie, <hi>excepto peccato omnia poteſt quae deus,</hi> excepting ſinne he can do al that God can doe. Alſo, <hi>papa poteſt quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid vult,</hi> the Pope can do what he wil, and therfore <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra novu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poteſt diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſare,</hi> he may diſpenſe againſt the new teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. From the Canoniſts I come to the Alcora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Franciſcans taken out of their booke of Conformities, <hi>nihil fecit Chriſtus, quod Franciſcus non fecit, imo plura fecit quàm Chriſtus, vngues Franciſci tentatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem propellunt, Chriſt did not any thing but Frances did the ſame, yea more then Chriſt, the nailes of frier Frances driue away temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. Sicut Ade Deo non parenti omnis creatura libellis extitit. Sic Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſco omnia praecepta diuina implenti creatura omnis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulata est, omnia Deus ſubiecit ſub pedibus eius, &amp;c.</hi> As euerie creature rebelled againſt Adam diſobeying God, ſo all of them ſerued Frances who fulfilled gods commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: God hath put all things vnder his feete, he hath made him ruler ouer all the workes of his handes, and he may moſt worthily ſay
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:12177:50"/> that which is written in the Goſpell, <hi>All things are giuen mee of my father:</hi> Can the diuel himſelfe ſpeake more ſpitefully againſt the God of heauen and earth? I wonder howe the Pope can ſuffer thoſe things, ſeing he applyeth the ſame ſcriptures to his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and therefore ſayeth, <hi>Omnis potestas mihi data est in terra, all power is giuen me on earth:</hi> To proceede in the ſame booke thus they ſpeake of the maſſe, <hi>Celebratio v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius miſſae tantum valet, quantum Chriſti paſsio, The ſaying of one maſſe is as profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as Chriſts paſsion.</hi> And againe, <hi>ſi quis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votè audierit miſſam non incidit in pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum mortale,</hi> if any here maſſe with deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he cannot fall into mortall ſinne, if this be true why haue the prieſts ſo many harlots? nay why are Popiſh geldings become ſtone horſes? Theſe (Chriſtian reader) are not the tenth of their blaſphemies which they haue vomited, but I dare not load thee with any more, leaſt I ſhould he offenſiue: I will ende this reaſon in a word: that religion is a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous religion which maketh not God mercifull, and iuſt in the higheſt degree, but
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:12177:51"/> the Popiſh religion maketh not God merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and iuſt in the higheſt degree: <hi>Ergo</hi> it is a blaſphemous religion: the aſſumption is thus prooued, if the onely mercie of God be not the onely cauſe of the pardoning of our ſinnes, and the alone ſatisfaction of Chriſt aunſwereth not to Gods iuſtice then may a finite thing, as mans ſatisfactions anſwer the ſame, &amp; ſo he ſhal neither be <hi>ſummè miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cors,</hi> nor <hi>ſummè iuſtus, neither haue perfect mercy,</hi> nor <hi>perfect iuſtice:</hi> but the only mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God is not the onely cauſe of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of our ſinnes, neither is his iuſtice fully ſatisfied by Chriſt, but by our owne ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction? and therefore he is neither perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly mercifull, not perfectly iuſt. Let god be then as he is is moſt rich in mercy and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute in iuſtice, and the Romiſh religion can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand, for it detracteth from his infinit mercy and iuſtice, therfore without all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie is a blaſphemous religion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="reason">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:12177:51"/>
            <head>The eight reaſon of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts owne Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt the properties of truth, this as I proued was one, that it was great and preuaileth, and indeed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Gods omnipotent power it is ſo great that the Aduerſaries againſt themſelues confeſſe the ſame: ſo that I may ſay with the Orator in his oration <hi>pro Quinctio: quis nostrae cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae testis idem qui accerrimus aduerſarius in hac re inquam adverſarium citabo testem: Who beareth witnes to our defence, euen he that is the fierceſt aduerſary in this defence:</hi> I ſay I will vſe our aduerſarie for a witnes, for although I may ſay to him as the ſame o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator doth in an other oration <hi>pro Fonteio: Tuum teſtimonium quod in aliena re leve est, in tua quoniam contrate eſt graviſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum eſſe debet: Thy ovvne teſtimonie which is of ſmall credit in another matter,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:12177:52"/> in thine owne becauſe it is against thy ſelfe ought to be of exceeding great waight:</hi> vpon theſe triumphs as it were the Chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will be deſirous to heare the Papiſts te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie, not to hold him therfore any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in ſuſpence, this is Bellarmines confeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in his 7. chap. &amp; 5. book of Iuſtification. <hi>Propter periculum maius gloriae tutiſsimum est fiduciam totam in ſola Dei miſericordia &amp; benignitate reponere:</hi> by reaſon of the danger of pride and vaine glorie, it is ſafeſt to put our whole confidence onely in the mercy of God, not in our merites or good workes. And this he prooueth out of the 9. chap. of Daniel, <hi>we pray not in our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but in thy manifold mercies:</hi> and out of the 17. of Luke, <hi>when you haue done all that you can, you are vnprofitable ſeruants:</hi> nay out of their owne praiers, <hi>Deus qui conſpicis quia ex nulla actione nostra confidimus: O God thou ſeest that vve trust not in any of our actions or vvorkes:</hi> and leaſt theſe his proofes ſhould not be waightie enough, he quoteth Chryſoſtome in diuers places, as namely in his 3. homily vpon Matthew wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:12177:52"/> thus: <hi>Noli mercedem poſcere vt accipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as mercedem,</hi> require no reward that thou maieſt receiue a rewarde. Next followeth Ambroſe, <hi>Non ſic vixi, vt me pudeat vive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, nec mori timeo quia bonum Dominum habemus; I haue ſo liued that I am not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to liue, neither am I afraide to die, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haue a mercifull Lord.</hi> After Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe followes Auguſtine, Gregorie, and Bernard: and laſtly he vſeth this reaſon: <hi>vel homo habet vera merita vel non habet,</hi> man hath good works in truth, or els he hath the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not in truth but in appearance onely, if onely in appearance then is he dangerouſly decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, if in truth then he looſeth nothing, for his truſt is onely in God. This is to diſanull all his former doctrine, for before he proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that a man might put his confidence in good workes, becauſe they deſerue eternall life; but now he confeſſeth that it is beſt to put no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence in works, but only in Gods mercie: out of which I conclude, that it is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to diſclaime our owne merits in the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to ſaluation, and by conſequent to be a Proteſtant. The ſyllogiſme ſhall be thus
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:12177:53"/> framed. It is ſafeſt to put no confidence in workes: but this is the Proteſtants conſtant doctrine: <hi>ergo</hi> it is ſafeſt to be a Proteſtant: and indeede it hath beene alwaies iudged the part of a wiſe man to encline <hi>in eam partem quae cautior est,</hi> into that defence which is beſt, but our defence is beſt by the aduerſaries own confeſsion: <hi>ergo</hi> it is the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt part to holde with the Proteſtants. So now I may iuſtly vſe the Orators exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his oration <hi>pro Coelio: ô magna vis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis quae contra hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ingenia, collidita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſolertia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c ô mighty power of truth, who doth defend it ſelfe againſt the wit, craft, &amp; ſubtiltie of men.</hi> I will end this reaſon with ſome ſayings of Hieron, becauſe his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie hath not bin yet vſed in this matter: in his 3. book againſt the Pelagians he writeth thus, <hi>Nec in ſapientia noſtra, nec in vllis virtutibus confidendum, ſed in ſolo domino: We truſt neither in our wiſdome, nor in any vertues, but onely in the Lord:</hi> and in his dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue againſt the Luciferians, <hi>Credo &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſecundum fidem meam fieri nolo, ſi ete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim ſit peribo: I beleeue, yet I vvould not
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:12177:53"/> haue it be according to my beleefe, for then I periſh:</hi> So muſt euery Chriſtian ſay if it be according to our workes wee periſh, but we truſt onely to the mercie of God: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore looke and waite for ſaluation. To this confeſsion of Bellarmine I might likewiſe haue adioyned <hi>Steuen Gardiners,</hi> but Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine being the papiſts <hi>Pythagoras</hi> ſhal ſerue in ſtead of all. And now for a concluſion of this point and reaſon, let any papiſt anſwer me what harme can come of the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts doctrine? if they ſay good works are come to a downefall by it, I would haue yeelded but that S. Paul in the 2. of the Galat. ver. 17. many hundered yeares agoe hath anſwered this rotten and ſtale obiection, <hi>If vve that ſeeke for iustification by Christ, be found ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in Chriſt, is Christ the minister of ſinn? God forbid, &amp;c.</hi> by which place of holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture this friuolous cauill is ſo plainely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed, that the Papiſts (except they cannot reſolue the Apoſtles argument) might as well haue charged Pauls doctrine with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutenes as they do ours, therfore I deſire all men to holde that which is ſafeſt, which is
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:12177:54"/> the part of a wiſe man to doe. But it is ſafeſt to hold as we hold, and it is the part of wiſe men to defende the beſt part, which is ours: <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is ſafeſt to hold with: and why was the Phariſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned vs but for putting his confidence in workes? he acknowledged them to come from God,<note place="margin">Luk. 18. v. 11</note> ſaying, <hi>I thanke thee that I am not as other men are, I faſt twiſe in a weeke, I giue tith of all that I haue.</hi> If we giue thanks to god for thoſe his good actions and workes, then by neceſſarie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent it may be concluded that he aſcribed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to himſelfe, but to the giuer &amp; foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of all good things, yet hath he Chriſts owne teſtimony againſt him for what the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but for his affiance in his workes. Thus the Papiſts by their owne doctrine of confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in workes become Phariſees: alſo I ſee not why they may not ſay to god as the Iewes did, why do we faſt, &amp; thou doeſt not regard vs? why doe we afflict out ſoules and thou doeſt not acknowledge vs? Better it is to pray with the Prophet Dauid, <hi>Enter not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to iudgement O Lord with thy ſeruants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 143. v. 3</note> 
               <hi>for no fleſh is righteous in thy ſight.</hi> To which
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:12177:54"/> place of Scripture Bellarmine anſwereth that it is to be vnderſtood,<note place="margin">Tom. <hi>1.</hi> lib de Mona. cap. <hi>13</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ad comparatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dei,</hi> in compariſon of God, and ſo conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelfe with the anſwer of Pelagius as I prooue out of Hierom in his booke <hi>ad Cteſip. Non iuſtificabitur in conſpectu Dei omnis vivens quod teſtimonium ſub nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne pietatis eludunt, aiunt enim ad compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem dei nullum eſſe perfectum, quaſi hoc dicat ſcriptura, quando enim dicit in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectu tuo hoc intelligi vult quod etiam qui hominibus ſancti videntur, dei ſcientiae at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que notitiae nequaquam ſunt ſancti.</hi> No ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liuing ſhall be iuſtified in thy ſight, which te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony vnder the prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of piety they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude, for they ſay that no man is perfect in reſpect of God, as if this were the meaning of the ſcripture, for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſaith (in thy ſight) it giueth vs to vnderſtand, that thoſe which ſeeme holy to men, in gods ſight and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge are not holy. Out of this teſtimony it appeareth that the papiſts accepting of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius his anſwer, ioyne not onely with the Phariſes in this point, but alſo with the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of whoſe hereſie I haue ſpoke before,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:12177:55"/> I dare not ſtay any longer in this reaſon, leſt I forget my ſelfe promiſing to haue ended it before, but the laying open of the Papiſts Phariſeiſme and Pelagianiſme <hi>I</hi> hope will ad ſome weight to it, and therefore I haue dwelt a little the longer in it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="reason">
            <head>The ninth reaſon of the pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Primitiue Church.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I might be very long in ſhewing the practiſe of the primitiue Church to be repugnant to popery, yet I will eude this reaſon with all poſsible brevity. Euſebius in his 4. booke of his Eccleſiaſticall hiſtory, and 14. chapter, writeth thus of the people of Smyrna, who by the malitious Iewes were eſteemed as worſhippers of Policarpus: <hi>Iudaei noſtros in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentis oculis obſervarunt, ne eum àflammis
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:12177:55"/> adhuc ardentibus raperent ignorantes, quia neque Chriſtum aliquando poſsemus dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquere, qui mortem pro totius mundi ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſuſtinuit, neque alium quenqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> colere quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam eum verum deum, &amp; qui ſolus colen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ſit noverimus, martyres vero tanquam deſcipulos diligimus quaſi integrè fidem ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtro ſeruantes &amp; domino, quorum nos quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que in fidei perſeverantia &amp; charitatis op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamus eſſe participes.</hi> The Iewes watched vs diligently leaſt we ſhould haue taken him out of the fire being ignorant, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we can leaue Chriſt which hath ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for all that are ſaued in the world, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhippe any other, for him we adore as beeing God, but the Martyrs as diſciples and fellowes of our Lord, we loue worthily for their exceeding good will vnto their king and maſter, of whoſe charitie in faith and perſeuerance God graunt we may be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers. This teſtimony ſheweth howe the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts are departed from this practiſe, who do not only loue, but moſt ſuperſtitiouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore the reliques of Saints: the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s were charged as you may ſee in <hi>Iuſtins</hi> 2. apo. to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:12177:56"/> be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, Atheiſts, not to worſhip God, to whom he anſwereth, <hi>Profitemur nos qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem talium qui habentur deorum eſſe exper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; atheos, ſed non veriſsimi illius dei pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris videlicet virtutum expertes, verum hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c ipſum &amp; qui ab illo venit filium, &amp; ſpiritum propheticum colimus &amp; adoramus cum rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one &amp; veritate venerantes. We profeſſe our ſelues to be vvithout ſuch as are accounted Gods, and indeed to be Atheiſts, but not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the moſt true God the father of vertues, for we worſhip and adore him and his ſonne, and the holy ghost in truth and as reaſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth.</hi> Out of which anſwer I gather that the Chriſtians did not worſhip Saints, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, or other things, for then Iuſtine might haue anſwered that the Chriſtians worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped many Gods, as the heathen did, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if they worſhipped as many as the Papiſts who exceed the Gentiles, or at leaſtwiſe are nothing behinde them in their idolatrie: and if theſe two will not content the Papiſts in this point.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>8.</hi> Booke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Celſum p. <hi>937.</hi>
               </note> let Origen ſpeak: <hi>Solus Deus ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randus est, preces offerendae ſoli vnigenito Dei verbo, qui vt pontifex eas ad Deum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:12177:56"/> &amp; Deum noſtrum perferat. God alone is to be adored, to the onely begotten ſonne of God our praiers are onely to be offered, vvho as high priest offereth them to his and our God.</hi> And againe, <hi>Oblitus cum Christianis ſe agere ſoli Deo per Ieſum preces offerentibus: Hee forgetteth himſelfe that he hath to doe with Christians who offer their praiers only to God by Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Theſe teſtimonies of Origen do euidently manifeſt vnto vs, what was the approoued vſe of the church in his time, <hi>viz.</hi> that their praiers were not made vnto Angels nor Saints, but onely to God in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, neither haue we the practiſe of the primitiue Church onely in this point but in many moe, which I will in a worde declare. The Chriſtians were charged by the Pagans for hauing no ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and they not onely confeſſed ſo much, but alſo defended it as moſt agreeable to the law of God. Origen, <hi>Contra Celſum lib.</hi> 8.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 934.</note> 
               <hi>posthaec Celſus ait nos ararum, statuarum, templorum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dedicationes fugere, non videns pro aris ſuam eſſe mentem cuique ex qua ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum feruntur verè &amp; intelligibiliter ſuaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olentes
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:12177:57"/> ſuffitus, ſimulachra autem Deo dican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da ſunt non fabrorum opera, ſed à verbo Dei dedolata &amp; formata in nobis, viz. virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ad imitationem primogeniti totius ei na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae, hae ſunt ſtatuae Deo dicatae. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more Celſus affirmeth that vvee haue no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of Altars, ſtanding Images and Temples, not knovving that euerie man in steede of an Altar hath a minde, out of vvhich are ſent ſpirituall ſvvet-ſmelling perfumes, and as touching Images ſuch are dedicated to god as are not the vvorkes of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificers, but are framed of the word of god in vs, namely vertues to the imitation of the first begotten of euery creature, thoſe are the images that are dedicated to god.</hi> Againe in his 7. booke pag. 928. <hi>Multa adeò nos prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent ab aris &amp; ſimulachris, vt emori citius iubeant, quàm contaminemus nostram de Deo fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> talibus impietatibus. There are ſo many prohibitions againſt Altars &amp; Images, that men are commaunded rather to die, then to defile their faith which they haue of god with ſuch impiety.</hi> Out of which two teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies as I conclude againſt images, ſo may
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:12177:57"/> I likewiſe againſt Altars, and then what will become of the popiſh ſacrifice of the maſſe? Not to reſt onely in the authoritie of Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen, heare what Clemens Alexandrinus ſaith in his exhortation to the Gentiles, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. Nobis non eſt imago ſenſilis de materia ſenſili, ſedquae percipitur intelligentia: Wee haue no image that is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall and ſeene vvith eyes, but onely ſuch as is conceaued with vnderſtanding:</hi> I let paſſe Lactantius his teſtimony becauſe I haue bin long in it before, and vſe Arnobius authority in whoſe 8. booke, the heathen do moue this queſtion, <hi>Cur nullas ar as habent nulla te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pla, nulla not a ſimulachra, why haue they no Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, no Temples, no knowen Images?</hi> of theſe teſtimonies I may ſay with the Orator, <hi>Aut hoc teſtium ſatis est aut neſcio quid ſatis eſt, Either theſe are ſufficient witneſſes, or els I know not what is ſufficient.</hi> But I come now to a third practiſe of the church repugnant and oppoſite to poperie, which was to haue publike praiers in a knowen tongue: Iuſtine in his ſecond apologie <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp; in ſolis qui dicitur die omnium qui vel in oppi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:12177:58"/> vel ruri degunt in eundem locum conuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus fit, &amp; commentaria Apostolorum, aut ſcripta Prophetarum leguntur, quo ad tempus patitur: On the day which is called Sunday all that are in townes or villages meet together in one place vvhere the writings of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles or Prophets are read as the houre per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth vs.</hi> When the reader ceaſeth, the parſon warneth and exhorteth vs to imitate the good things that haue bin read vnto vs, then ariſe we all &amp; ioyntly make our praiers after which ended, bread and wine with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter are brought to the place, and he that is chiefe amongſt vs giueth thanks in the beſt manner he can: and a litle before, <hi>Perfectis precibes &amp; gratiarum actione, populus omnis qui adest bene dicit dicens Amen:</hi> at the ende of his praiers and thanks, all the people that are preſent do bleſſe and ſay <hi>Amen. Amen</hi> in hebrew ſignifieth as much as God graunt it may bee ſo. If they deſire plainer words let them heare Origen <hi>lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cont. Celſum pag.</hi> 941. <hi>Sciant quod germanè Chriſtiani, ne vſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis quidem Dei nominibus in ſacra ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura vtuntur inter precandum, ſed Graeci
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:12177:58"/> Graecis, Romani Romanis, ſingulique precan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in propria lingua, deum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> celebrant pro viribus, &amp; omnium linguarum Dominus, omni bus linguis precantes exaudit tàm va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riè loque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes haud ſecus ac co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſonos &amp;c.</hi> Let me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knowe that true Chriſtians doe not vſe in their praiers the names of god which are v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in holy ſcripture, but greeks do vſe greek names, Romanes vſe Latine names, and men of euery nation pray and praiſe god with all their might in theit owne mother tongue, and the Lord of al tongues doth heare them praying in all tongues vnderſtanding them that ſpeake diuerſly no otherwiſe then if they were men of one ſpeech and language. I might here alleadge the 15. Canon of the Councell of Laodicia which ordained that none ſhould ſing but thoſe that were Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nically elected, <hi>&amp; qui de Codice legunt,</hi> and thoſe that read out of their books, by which it appeareth that ſome of the people could reade the Pſalmes and by conſequent had them in their owne tongue. But let Baſill ende the third difference, who writeth,<note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>80.</hi> ad Caterineo.</note> that in the church the people did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:12177:59"/> that is, anſwer one another in ſinging: and this was the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner and cuſtome of all chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>mos qui nunc obtinet omnibus Dei Eccleſiis conſonus est &amp; conſentaneus: the cuſtome which novve preuaileth is agreeable to all churches:</hi> and after this he rehearſeth the Aegyptians, The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans, Arabians, Syrians, and Chaldaeans. So then now I hold it needeles in ſo cleare and manifeſt a matter, to quote mo teſtimonies, for I might haue vſed Auguſtines, Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, Hieromes, and Ambroſes authority for the proofe of this practiſe, but eſchuing tediouſnes I will now propound the fourth Difference. The people in the primitiue Church were not depriued of the cuppe in the Communion, ſo teſtifieth Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinus,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Some distributing the Euchariſt doe ſuffer the people as the custome is to take part.</hi> This teſtimonie alſo ouerthroweth the prieſts priuate Communion, which I might haue made an other difference, but that for breuitie ſake I ſpare to ſpeake of it. To Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:12177:59"/> I adioyne Iuſtine in his 2. Apol. <hi>qui a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud nos diaconi vocantur dant vnicuique eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum qui adſunt partem panis pro quo gratia actae ſunt &amp; vini &amp; aquae participandam: they which we call deacons giue to all that are preſent a part of conſecrated bread and wine mingled with water to be receiued.</hi> Here I might abound with teſtimonies, and time would ſooner faile me then proofes, and therefore I take and accept the confeſsion of Duraeus, who beeing preſſed with the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Gelaſius, who commanded that ſacraments ſhould be either wholly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued or wholly omitted, confeſſeth that for foure hundred yeeres it was ſo vſed in the Church, I will not ſtand to ſhew that it was longer continued, but I demand why that which was ſo long practiſed in the Church, ſhould be diſanulled by the Counſell of Conſtance, were the Fathers in that counſel wiſer then all the Chriſtians in ſo many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, yea then the Apoſtles and Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? The fift difference is that the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were hot burdened with many feſtiuall daies:<note place="margin">936. p.</note> Celſus obiecting to the Church the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:12177:60"/> want of feaſts is anſwered by Origen, <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum</hi> is <hi>facere officium</hi> id eſt, <hi>a feast is to doe a duty,</hi> &amp; proueth it out of the fourth of the Galat: that daies are not to be kept excepting the Lordes day, Eaſter and Pentecoſt, what then is become of the multitude of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh feſtiuall daies wherewith the Church is grieuouſly burdened, concerning this point Eraſmus writeth thus vpon Matthew 11. cap. <hi>Aetas Hieronimi praeter diem do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicum p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ifsima noverat festa. In Hierom his time there vvas very fevve fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiuall daies beſides the Lords day.</hi> And in the tripartite hiſtory in the ninth booke, &amp; the thirtie eight chapter I finde theſe wordes, <hi>Mens fuit Apostolorum non de diebus ſanci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re festivitatem, ſed converſatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rectam &amp; Dei praedicare culturam: It vvas not the Apostles meaning to giue lavves concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning festiuall daies, but to preach a holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation and the worſhip of God.</hi> To leaue this practiſe and come to the ſixt difference namely of faſting. I finde likewiſe that the Church left it free, and impoſed no neceſsity vpon men to obſerue the Lent faſt, <hi>Quidam</hi>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:12177:60"/> ſaith Euſebius) <hi>putant vno tantum die obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vari debere ieiunium, alii duobus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 24</note> 
               <hi>alij vero pluribus, nonnulli etiam quadraginta, ita vt horas diurnas nocturnaſque computantes diem ſtatuant; ſome thought they ought to faſt one day, ſome two daies, ſome more, ſome fourtie daies, and counting the houres of the day and night, make vp the daye.</hi> Alſo, <hi>Ieiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nii diſſolentia fidei vnitatem commendat. The diuerſitie of faſting commendeth the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of faith.</hi> To Euſebius agreeth Socrates ſaying, <hi>in ipſis ieiunijs aliter apud alios ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruari inuenimus, Romani enim tres an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Paſcha ſeptimanas ieiunant, tota Hellas, Alexandria quoque ſex ſeptimanas antè ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunant. We finde difference in the obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of faſts themſelues, the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s faſt three weekes before Eaſter, all Greece and Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria</hi> 6. <hi>weekes.</hi> Memorable is the practiſe of Spirid. in the ſame hiſt. 1. lib. 12. cap. who ſaid that <hi>omnia munda mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dis, al things are clean to the cleane:</hi> &amp; therefore in <hi>quadrageſsima edebat carnes porcinas, In lent he fed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con.</hi> Laſtly good is the aduiſe of Nazi. in his oration of Baptiſme: <hi>Chriſtus quadraginta
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:12177:61"/> dies ieiunavit, nos noſtris viribus men ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Chriſt fasted forty daies, let vs meaſure it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our ability.</hi> Out of all theſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies it is apparent to all men that there was no vniformity in faſting, and therefore the Papiſts are degenerate in this point alſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the primitiue Church, becauſe they impoſe a neceſsity of abſtinence from fleſh permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting fiſh, for (as we may reade in the places before cited) ſome vſed to feed on fleſh in the time of lent. Many moe differences, as namely the libertie of miniſters in marriage, the reading of the ſcriptures &amp;c. might I haue ſtood vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but for breuity ſake hoping that theſe differences here recited will ſatisfy a Chriſtian, I leaue them, and ſay with our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>It was not ſo from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mtah. 19. v. 8</note> as the Papiſts would beare me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, and therefore they are to reforme their reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, for as Cyprian ſaith ad Pomp. <hi>con ſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo ſine veritate vetuſtas erroris eſt: cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome without trueth is but an auncient er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="reason">
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:12177:61"/>
            <head>The tenth reaſon of Scripture.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I ſhould in this reaſon proſecute all thinges that argue the deſperate caſe of popiſh religion, my treatiſe would exceede the meaſure of the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume which I propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to my ſelfe: therefore in a word I come firſt to the abuſing of Scripture by vngodly tranſlations. In the 1. chapter of the epiſtle to the Hebrewes, &amp; 3. verſe, it is ſaid, <hi>that Chriſt purged our ſinnes by himſelfe,</hi> which words <hi>(by himſelfe)</hi> are cleane ſtricken out, as ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing their blaſphemous doctrine of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions: for they teach, that Chriſt ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by the repentant, whereas the Scripture ſaieth, that hee ſatisfieth by himſelfe. In the ſame Epiſtle, the 7. chapter, and 28. verſe, it is written, that the law appointeth prieſts men that haue infirmity, but the word of the oth which is after the lawe, the ſonne for euer
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:12177:62"/> perfected: where by the oppoſition it is moſt cleare, that Ieſus Chriſt is a Prieſt as hee is God. Yet they contrarie to their latine tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation haue left out the word <hi>[men]</hi> that the oppoſition might not appeare. Againe, in the thirteene chapter and 16. verſe: their tranſlation is thus, <hi>vvith ſuch hoſtes God is promerited:</hi> doth not this make for their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of deſeruing at Gods hands? where as it is in the greeke fountaine, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is, <hi>vvith ſuch ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces god is delighted, or vvell pleaſed.</hi> To what a deſperate eſtate are theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grown, which ſo wilfully againſt their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, in fauour of their hereſies, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate the Scripture. Is there no difference betwixt pleaſing of God, and meriting? All the ſubſtances and qualities of things natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, pleaſe God becauſe they are good, yet doe they not deſerue at God his hands. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the fourteene chapter of Saint Iohn and the twentie ſixe verſe their tranſlation hath it thus, <hi>Suggeret vobis omnia quaecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dixero vobis,</hi> which they finely engliſh thus, <hi>Shall ſuggeſt vnto you whatſoeuer I ſhall ſay
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:12177:62"/> vnto you,</hi> when they knowe the greek hath <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>all things vvhich I haue ſpoken vnto you.</hi> Is not this tranſlated to maintaine the traditions of their Church, and decrees of Popes, and counſailes? That it is ſo, it appeareth by their note, referring the reader to the 16. chapter, and 12. verſe. Vpon which they haue gathered their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions: but Saint Auguſtine vpon that verſe anſwereth them, <hi>Cum ipſe tacuerit, vvhen he himſelfe hath not vttered theſe things, vvhich of vs can ſay, theſe, and theſe they are? or if he dare be ſo bold to ſay, hovv doth he prooue it?</hi> In the tenth chapter of Luke &amp; the thirtie fiue verſe, the vulgar latine hath it thus, <hi>Quodcunque ſuperogaueris, ego cum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diero, reddam tibi,</hi> which they haue tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thus, <hi>whatſoeuer thou ſhalt ſupererogate &amp;c.</hi> Hence are gathered works of ſuperero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, it is in the greeke: <hi>whatſoeuer thou ſpendest more.</hi> Theſe (to ſpeake the leaſt of them) are both ſupererogant collections, and ſuperarogant works. To proceed in the 11. of the Rom. and 6. verſe, theſe words are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, <hi>but if it bee of vvorks, it is no more
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:12177:63"/> of grace, or els were worke no vvorke,</hi> the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing out of this ſentence, helpeth their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of merits, let it alone in the ſcripture, and grace and merits cannot ſtand together: for here we may gather, that <hi>gratia non est vllo modo gratia, niſiſit omni modo gratuita, grace is not grace except it be euery way free.</hi> In the 5. to the Epheſ. they tranſlate <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum hoc magnum est, this is a great Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament:</hi> Out of which the maiſter of the Sentences <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>distinct.</hi> 26. prooueth mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to be a Sacrament: the greeke is, <hi>This is a great miſterie, or ſecret,</hi> which Saint Paul ſpeaketh, and meaneth of Chriſt, and his Church. (Not to quote many teſtimonies) let Cyprian that famous Martyr ſpeak in his 2. booke of Epiſt. the 8. epiſt. <hi>Cum Apoſtolus dicit Sacramentum, hoc magnum eſt Chriſti, pariter &amp; Eccleſiae vnitatem indiuiduis nex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ibus cohaerentem, ſancta ſua voce testatur, When the Apostle ſaieth this is a great Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament he teſtifieth the vnitie of Christ &amp; his holy Church knitt together, with vndiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible bondes. I</hi> cannot let paſſe that intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tranſlation, Romanes the ſeuenth and the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:12177:63"/> 25. verſe. Where S. Paule crying out, <hi>O mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from this body of ſinne?</hi> in the next verſe they tranſlate, <hi>the grace of Chriſt,</hi> conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of it, that grace is ſufficient to reſiſt temptations and to vanquiſh ſinne, where the Apoſtle ſaith no more, but <hi>I thanke god,</hi> yet they make the meaning to be this, who ſhall deliuer me from this body of death? the the grace of God by Ieſus Chriſt; whereas there is no ſuch meaning: for Paul hauing ſorrowed for his ſinne, reſted in the hope which he had placed in Chriſt. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more in the 1. to the Corinth. the ninth cap. and 5. verſe, they haue peruerted S. Pauls wordes, whereas he ſayeth, a ſiſter, a wife, or (as they would haue it) a ſiſter, a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they make it to be a woman, a ſiſter, expounding it againſt the Apoſtles wiues, whereas no man would ſay a ſiſter, a woman, becauſe the word ſiſter implieth a woman. We read indeede that certaine women did fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt, we read not that he led them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout.<note place="margin">vide Euſeb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um lib. <hi>3.</hi> ca. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> Concerning this matter Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinus writeth thus. <hi>An &amp; Apoſtolos
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:12177:64"/> improbant? Petrus enim ac Philippus vxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res habuerunt. Doe they diſalovv the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles? for Peter and Philip had wiues.</hi> And it grieueth not Paul in a certaine epiſtle to ſpeake of his yoake-fellow, which he did not lead about with him, that he might be more readie to preach the goſpel. But to come to a waightie matter indeede, they tranſlate the 2. verſe of the 3. chap. of Matth. <hi>Doe penance,</hi> which cannot be ſo turned, and that I prooue by theſe reaſons: Firſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> includeth in it confeſsion of ſinnes, and ſatisfaction for ſinnes: but the baptized are not bounde to confeſſe and ſatisfie for their ſinnes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aquin.</hi> 3. <hi>p. q.</hi> 68. <hi>ar.</hi> 5, 6.</note> yet they muſt repent: therefore to confeſſe and ſatisfie, is not to repent. The <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſecond reaſon is this: that the Rhemiſts wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpon the firſt of Mark and 12. v. faith, that <hi>Christ did penance,</hi> therefore a man may doe penance without ſorow for ſinnes, or elſe Chriſt repented of his ſinnes which <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> is moſt horrible blaſphemie. Thirdly let Lactantius ſpeake <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>reſipi ſcentia di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>nam mentem quaſi ab inſania reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit. The Greeke word is called Repentance,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:12177:64"/> for it recouereth the minde (as it were) from follie.</hi> Fourthly, Act. the 5. chap. and 31. verſ. they tranſlate it themſelues, <hi>Repentance,</hi> and againe Marke the 1. chap. and 15. verſe, <hi>be penitent.</hi> I will not ſtand vpon any moe places in the newe Teſtament, but come to a fewe of the olde. In the ninth of the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher and ſecond verſe they haue theſe wordes, <hi>Omnia in futurum ſervantur in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certa, All things are reſerued as vncertain for the future time:</hi> there is no ſuch thing in the Hebrew, yet out of this place is proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the vncertentie of ſaluation and finall perſeuerance. O moſt wretched and vile doctrine that muſt coyne ſcripture to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende it ſelfe! In the 98. pſalme and 5. verſe they tranſlate, <hi>vvorſhippe his footestoole, for it is holy,</hi> and from hence conclude the ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and worſhipping of creatures, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it ſhould haue beene turned, <hi>at his foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoole he is holy, lahadom</hi> the ſame thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing repeated in the laſt verſe. In the 8. of Geneſis toward the ende of the chap. where it ſhould be, <hi>the thoughts of mans heart
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:12177:65"/> are euill,</hi> in their tranſlation it is <hi>prone to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill,</hi> as if there were no difference betwixt prone to euill, and euill, If I ſhould affirme a papiſt to be prone to euill, and treaſon, doe I ſay that he is euill, and treaſon it ſelfe? no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe: euen ſo there is a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt proneſſe to vice, and vice it ſelfe. In the 14. of Geneſis, and 18. verſe, they haue it thus <hi>erat enim ſacerdos dei altiſsimi, for he was a prieſt of the moſt high God,</hi> in fauour of their ſacrifice: where it is, <hi>and he vvas a prieſt of the high God,</hi> neither let them aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere me that the coniunction <hi>(vau)</hi> doeth ſometimes ſignifie (for) that is not the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but whether it ſo ſignifieth in this place. And becauſe they vaunte of antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in this point, Freculph. in the firſt booke of his hiſtorie, and 42 chap. ſaith, that <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizedech, in refectionem ipſius Abrahae, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, vinumque protulit. Melchizedech brought forth bread and wine for the refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of Abraham.</hi> I will follow this matter of tranſlations no further at this time. By this euery one may gather why they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the pure Hebrewe, and Greeke foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:12177:65"/> and drinke of the corrupt Latin ſtreames.</p>
            <p>I come in the ſecond place to the denial of plaine Scriptures. In the 3. of the Galat. and 10. ver. it is thus written, <hi>for as many as are of the deedes of the law, are vnder the curſe: for it is written, curſed is euery one that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth not in all things that are written in the booke of the law, to doe them:</hi> in which words the Apoſtle doth thus reaſon,
<q>
                  <p>They which cannot fulfill the law are vnder the curſe:</p>
                  <p>But no man can fulfill the law: <hi>ergo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>If this be not the Apoſtles aſſumption, the Galatians might haue anſwered Paul, that they could fulfil the law, and therefore were not vnder the curſe. Yet the Papiſts teach, that man may fulfil Gods law, and ſo cut the ſinewes of S. Pauls reaſon. Secondly in the 4. to the Rom. and 11. verſe, circumciſion is called <hi>a ſeale of the righteouſnes of faith:</hi> out of which place we gather, that we are not iuſtified by the ſacraments. The Papiſts to elude the place, anſwer it followeth not that it is ſo in all, becauſe it was ſo in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs;
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:12177:66"/> this anſwer diſioynteth the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles argument, which is this:
<q>
                  <p>As Abraham was iuſtified, ſo are all men iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified:</p>
                  <p>But Abraham was iuſtified without the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments:</p>
                  <p>Therefore all men are ſo iuſtified.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In the 6. of the Rom. and 27. ver. it is ſaide that <hi>the gift of God is eternall life, through Ieſus Christ our Lord.</hi> S. Pauls ſpeach is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the Rhemiſts, ſaying, the ſequele of the ſpeach required, that as he ſaide, death or damnation is the ſtipend of ſinne, ſo life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting is the ſtipende of iuſtice. To ſee papiſts ſit as it were in iudgement of the Scriptures, to alow, or diſalow ſentences at their pleaſure, is the moſt notorious exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Hereticall pride and miſerie that can be. Againe, in the 6. to the Rom. and 12. v. <hi>concupiſcence is called ſinne,</hi> yet denied by them to be ſinne. If the ſcripture had ſo ſaid, they might well haue expounded it as they doe, namely the occaſions and matter of ſinne. But ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not one thing be properly ſinne, and the occaſion of ſinne? let Auguſtine then
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:12177:66"/> be controlled, who in his 5. book <hi>contra Iul. Pelag.</hi> and 3. chap. writeth thus, <hi>Sicut caecitas cordis, &amp; peccatum est, &amp; poena peccati, &amp; cauſa peccati: it a concupiſcentia, carnis &amp; peccatum est, quia inest illi inobedientia contra dominatum mentis, &amp; poena peccati, &amp; cauſa peccati. As blindnes of heart is ſinn, and a puniſhment of ſinne, and a cauſe of ſinn: ſo likewiſe is concupiſcence ſinne, becauſe it diſobeieth the rule of the minde, and a puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhment of ſinne, and a cauſe of ſinne.</hi> Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines ſyllogiſme is this: That which is diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the gouernment of the minde is ſinne: But concupiſcence is diſobedience to the gouernement of the minde: Therefore concupiſcence is ſinne.</p>
            <p>Alſo in the 5. of the Roman. and 14. verſ. Paul prooueth all men to be ſinners, becauſe of death; yet is the virgin Marie exempted from ſinne, which ſtrengtheneth Pelagius his opinion. For he might denie the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Infants die, therefore they are no ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, becauſe Marie died, and yet was no ſinner. In the 1. to the Corinthians and 10. chap. S. Paul beateth downe the conceit of
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:12177:67"/> the Corinthians co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the ſacraments. For the Iewes did eate Chriſt in their ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Yet the Papiſts will haue our ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to giue grace <hi>ex opere operato, of the worke wrought,</hi> and ſo make the Apoſtles argument to be of no force. For the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians might haue replied, our ſacraments giue grace to them that receiue them, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we cannot be diſmaied, with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of the Iſraelites. Furthermore in the 9. of the Hebrewes the 25. verſ. Chriſt is ſaid <hi>to haue offered himſelfe but once,</hi> becauſe he ſuffered but once. The Apoſtles reaſon is this: <hi>Christ died but once: Therefore he ſuffered but once.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, Hebr. 10. and 8. ver. the Apoſtles concluſion is, <hi>ſeeing there is remiſsion of ſinnes, there is no more offering for ſinne.</hi> Therefore it followeth inuincibly, that the maſſe is not a ſacrifice for ſinne. Yet the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts aſſertion muſt needes fruſtrate both theſe arguments of the Apoſtle. From the deniall of ſcripture I come to the addition of the ſame, which argueth extreame deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atenes. The Councell of Laodicea 59. ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:12177:67"/> reiecteth the books which we doe and commandeth <hi>ne aliqui praeterea legantur, &amp; in authoritatem recipiantur, that non be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides be read, and receiued into authority.</hi> Ruffinus likewiſe in his expoſition vpon the Creede, reiecteth the ſame, and will not haue them alleadged, <hi>ad authoritatem fidei confirmandam, for the confirmation of faith.</hi> Cirill of Hieruſalem in the 4. booke of his Catech. writeteth thus. <hi>Lege ſcripturas ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cras nempè viginti duos veteris teſtamenti libros, read the holy ſcriptures, namely the two and twentie bookes of the old teſtament.</hi> I paſſe ouer Hieroms authority, and Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzens, with Euſebius, Epiphanius, and Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raes: If al theſe will not mooue them, yet let their Angelicall doctor Thomas Aquinas be of ſome force with them, who in his firſt <hi>part.</hi> 89. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 8. <hi>artic. reſp. ad ſecund.</hi> regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not the authoritie of Eccleſiaſticus. Fourthly and laſtly the concealing of the ſcriptures from the people, what end hath it, but maintenance of the Idolatrie, pompe, pride and couetouſnes of the popiſh prieſts
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:12177:68"/> and prelats, (as Eraſmus ſaith) <hi>Quis non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligat istos, ſacras literas ideo velle paucis eſſe notas ne quid decedat ipſorum authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti questuique? who knoweth not that theſe men would haue the ſcriptures knowne but to few, leaſt their authority and gaine ſhould decay?</hi> How could men be deceiued with I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, and robbed with Purgatory, if they were conuerſant in the ſcriptures. Thus Chriſtian reader I haue giuen thee a taſt of foure-notorious-crimes, namely corrupt tranſlations, deniall of plaine ſcriptures, addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them, and laſtly concealing them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the people: a taſt I ſay I haue giuen thee, for I could not proſecute them as the things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. If any Papiſt could ſhewe the like in the Calviniſts, what exclamations ſhould we haue? Maſter Martins diſcouery of our tranſlations argueth either blinde ignorance or extreame malice, as I offer to prooue to any Papiſt. Campian in his firſt reaſon obiecteth diffidence, and diſtruſt, becauſe we denie ſcriptures, therefore it is a ſure concluſion againſt them, they adde to the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:12177:68"/> Scripture and ſo diſtruſt their cauſe: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they could not adde any Apocripha books, as they doe: but inough of this.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="reason">
            <head>The eleuenth reaſon of popiſh contradictions.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He number of popiſh co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions is ſo great (as by reading of Bellarmine himſelfe euery man may gather) that I may ſaye with the Orator, <hi>In hac cauſa oratio nemini de eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe poteſt, In this matter no man can want words,</hi> &amp; therefore, <hi>non tàm mihi copia, quàm modus in dicendo quaerendus eſt, In ſpeaking of this thing I must ſeeke for a iust meaſure, not for plentie and varietie of matter.</hi> Chra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtouius in his book, called <hi>Bellum Ieſuiticum, the Ieſuites warre,</hi> beſides contradictions concerning Antichriſt hath gathered two hundred and fiftie about the Maſſe. Thus the Papiſts like the Madianites wound on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:12177:69"/> and indeed, <hi>Non tanta nobiſcum, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſecum est contentio, The controuerſie is not ſo great with vs as with themſelues,</hi> and this agreeth to the wonted and accuſtomed dealing of the Lord: who did, <hi>Haereticos in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſe committere, ſet hereticks togither by the eares:</hi> For (as Hierome ſaieth) Amos the 9. <hi>Niſi ſuperbiam haereticorum ſuo dominus calcauerit pede, &amp; peruerſam ſceleratamque doctrinam, ſpirituali mucrone percuſſerit, &amp; magistros eorum qui in capitibus accipiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, inter ſe diui ſerit, atque in bonam partem occiderit, non poſſunt diſcipuli viuificari, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Lord tyed dovvne the pride of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks with his foote, and wound their peruerſe and wicked doctrin with his ſpiritual ſword, and ſet their maſters which are counted the principallat diſſention, and ſlay them for the most part, their ſchollers cannot bee restored to life.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The firſt contradiction.</head>
               <p>The Papiſts teach that the Pope, as he is Pope cannot erre in giuing of ſentence, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he may erre as a priuate perſon, yet Alphonſus who wrote bitterly againſt Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:12177:69"/> when it came to this point, giueth the Papiſts both the crime of impudencie, and flatterie. <hi>Non credo aliquem adeo eſſe impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentem papae aſſentatorem, vt ei attribuere hoc velit, vt nec errare poſſit: I cannot thinke any man to be ſo impudent a flatterer of the Pope, as to attribute this vnto him that hee cannot erre:</hi> out of theſe words I gather firſt that the papiſts are the Popes flatterers, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that their flattery is ioyned with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudencie, which are two no ſmall faultes: to goe foreward in Alphonſus <hi>Caelestinum pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pam erraſſe circa matrimonium fidelium, quorum alter labitur in haereſim, res est ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſta omnibus, neque hic Caeleſtini error ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis fuit, qui ſoli negligentiae imputari debuit, ita vt illum erraſſe dicamus veluti priuatam perſonam, &amp; non vt Papam, quoniam huiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi Caelestini definitio habebatur in anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis decretalibas, &amp;c. It is a thing manifest to all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that Pope Caeleſtinus erred touching the marriage of the faithfull, vvhen either part fell into hereſie, neither was the error of Caelestinus ſuch, as ought to be imputed onely to negligence, ſo that wee may ſay he erred as
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:12177:70"/> a priuate perſon, not as a Pope, becauſe this definition of Caelestinus was in the auncient decretalls, vvhich I my ſelfe haue ſeene and read.</hi> In this ſentence Alphonſus confuteth the diſtinction vſed by the papiſts, namely that the Pope may erre as a priuate man, but not in a definitiue deciſion of a matter: but I would gladly knowe the cauſe why they hold that the Pope cannot iudicially erre? Is it not by reaſon of Chriſts praier? Luke 22. verſe 32. who prayed that Peters faith might not faile; ſuch ſenſleſſe diſputes are not worth an anſwer: yet if they will be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied let Cyprian ſatisfie them, who writeth thus in his 4. booke of Epiſt. and 4. Epiſt. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deo autem pro nobis deprecabatur, vt lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in alio loco,</hi> Luc. 12. <hi>Dixit Dominus ad Petrum &amp;c. Quodſi ille pro nobis ac delictis nostris laborat &amp; prec. &amp;c. He prayed ſo for us, as we read in another place, namly</hi> Luk. 12. <hi>the Lord ſaid vnto Peter, &amp;c. If he doth pray ſo for vs and our ſinnes, how much more ought we to continue in praier?</hi> By this expoſition and collection of Cyprian wee may gather that no chriſtian can erre iudicially, if that
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:12177:70"/> were the intent of Chriſt his prayers to free the Pope from giuing any definitiue ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce againſt the faith, for Chriſt prayeth for all Chriſtians and therfore we thus conclude.</p>
               <p>He for whome Chriſt prayeth cannot erre: But Chriſt prayeth for all true Chriſtians:</p>
               <p>Therefore no Chriſtian can erre.</p>
               <p>No papiſt I am aſſured will graunt the propoſition ſeing the aſſumption cannot be denied, being ſo plainly auouched by Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: but I proceed to the ſecond Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>2.</hi> Contradiction.</head>
               <p>The Papiſts nowe teach that the Pope is aboue a councel. <hi>Qui tradunt</hi> (ſaith the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian) <hi>concilium eſſe ſupra papam illi naturae repugnant, quum hoc nihil aliud ſit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 294.</note> 
                  <hi>quam partem toti praeferre. They that deliuer this doctrine that a councel is aboue a pope, croſſe nature, ſeeing this is nothing elſe but to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre a part before the whole.</hi> If this be true, then the counſell of Baſill oppoſeth it ſelfe to nature, for I finde it written in the 33. ſeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Veritas de proteſtate concilii generalis
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:12177:71"/> vniuerſalem eccleſiam repreſentantis, ſupra papam &amp; quemlibet alterum declarata, per Constantienſe, &amp; hoc Baſilienſe generaliae concilia, est veritas fidei Catholicae.</hi> The truth of the power of a generall Councell, repreſenting the vniuerſall Church, aboue the Pope and euery other perſon, declared by the generall councells of Conſtance, and this of Baſill, is the veritie of the Catholicke faith. And to retort Turrian his reaſon, thus may an argument be framed:
<q>
                     <p>The whole is aboue the part:</p>
                     <p>But the general Councell is the whole re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the vniuerſal Church:</p>
                     <p>Therefore it is aboue the Pope.</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>3.</hi> Contradiction.</head>
               <p>The Papiſts teach that neceſſarie argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may be drawne from traditions, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells, Popes decrees, and I know not what, and therefore wanting arguments againſt vs, obtrude their pelfe of traditions, which haue no warrant in the booke of God: yet Aquinas writeth otherwiſe, <hi>Sacra doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:12177:71"/> authoritatibus canonicae ſcripturae vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ex neceſsitate argumentando,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">parte <hi>1.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> art. <hi>8.</hi> reſp. ad <hi>2 <hi rend="sup">um</hi>.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus autem aliorum doctorum eccleſie quaſi arguendo non ex propriis, ſed probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus:</hi> Diuinitie vſeth the authoritie of the Canonicall ſcripture, arguing out of it by by neceſſarie arguments, but the authoritie of other church teachers, arguing as it were by proper, not by probable arguments. I wiſh the Papiſts would attend to their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Doctor in this point, which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſoundly out of Auguſtine: <hi>Solis enim ſcripturarum libris qui Canonici appellan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, didici hunc honorem deferre, vt nullum authorem eorum in ſcribendo erraſſe ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid firmiſsimè credam.</hi> For I haue learned to deferre this honour onely to the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall Scriptures, to beleeue moſt ſteadfaſtly that no Author of them hath erred in any point. If this were the opinion of all papiſts, many controuerſies would be compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded betwixt them and vs, yet this is in truth to honour and reuerence the Scriptures, which were good for all papiſts, and not to diſgrace them as they doe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:12177:72"/>
               <head>The <hi>4.</hi> Contradiction.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Praefat. To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia.</note>
                  <hi>Postquam auxiliante deo</hi> (ſaith Lyra) <hi>ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſi ſuper libros Canonicos ſacrae Scripturae, incipiendo à principio Geneſ. &amp; progredien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do vſque ad finem, eiuſdem confiſus auxilio ſuper alios intendo ſcribere, qui non ſunt de Canone, lib. Sapientiae, Eccleſiastic. Iudith, Tobiae, &amp; Macchabaeorum, &amp;c.</hi> After that by Gods aſsiſtance I haue written vpon the bookes of Canonicall ſcripture, from the beginning of Geneſis and ſo forward to the ende, truſting ſtill vnto his helpe, I purpoſe to write vpon thoſe that are not Canonical, as the booke of Wiſdome, Eccleſiaſticus, Iudith, Tobias, and the Maccabees. This is Lyra his opinion concerning theſe bookes, which he prooueth out of Hierom, and yet the Papiſts plead for them to be numbered amongſt the Canonicall Scriptures, yea (as thou heardeſt before) Campian in his firſt reaſon prooueth that we diſtruſt our cauſe, becauſe we denie them to be of equall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie with the other bookes; I paſſe by the authoritie of other Papiſts, as namely
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:12177:72"/> Hugo the Cardinall, and Caietan, who with Lyra cut theſe bookes from the bodie of the Bible, yet we may not doe ſo without here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and accuſation of mayming the holy Scriptures; let them now turne their pennes againſt their owne fellowes. Here I might haue made an other article of diſſention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the corruption of Scriptures: for Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danus and other Papiſts holde them to be corrupt, but the contrarie is learnedly taught by Iſacke, and Arrias Montanus, two fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Hebricians, and by Gods aſsiſtance I offer to defend it againſt all Papiſts, that are of another minde. Bellarmines reaſons are blowne away with a blaſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>5.</hi> Contradiction.</head>
               <p>There are ſo many opinions of Papiſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout marriage, that they themſelues are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine what to hold. This is witneſſed by Melchior Canus, <hi>lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>fol.</hi> 245. <hi>in ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio. Lege Magiſtrum, Diuum Thomam, Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, Bonavent. Richard Paludan. Durandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, caeteroſque ſcholae theologos, &amp; niſi ſtatim pendentes &amp; vacillantes eorum animos de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deris,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:12177:73"/> tum verò me aut stultum, aut te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merarium iudicato, nam &amp; cum quaerunt, an matrimonium conferat gratiam, idque eo loco maximè finiendum erat, non definiunt tamen, ſed in his referunt, quae in hominum opinione poſita ſunt. In materia aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma huius ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti statuenda, adeò ſunt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtantes, &amp; varii, adeò incerti, &amp; ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gui, vt ineptus futurus ſit, qui in tanta illoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> varietate, ac diſcrepantia, rem aliquam cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, constantem, &amp; exploratam conetur ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficere, quod ſi in forma, &amp; materia ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, &amp;c.</hi> Read the Maſter of Sentences, Saint Thomas, Bonaventure, Richardus Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludanus, Durandus, and the reſt of the ſchoole diuines, and if forthwith thou doeſt not finde their wauering and doubtfull mindes, then iudge me either a foole or a raſh fellow: for when they diſpute whether matrimonie giueth grace, that which was eſpecially to be determined, they doe not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine at all, but onely make relation of mens opinions, and in ſetting downe the matter and forme of this ſacrament, they are ſo inconſtant, ſo variable, ſo vncertaine, and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:12177:73"/> doubtfull, that he ſhall be iudged indiſcreete, who in ſuch a varietie, and diſcent, goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to frame any certaine &amp; conſtant mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But if they be ſo doubtful about the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and forme of the ſacrament, which is a matter of exceeding great moment &amp;c. Thus the Papiſts bare witneſſe one againſt another, concerning their pretended ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of marriage: and whoſoeuer readeth Bellarmine, out of this point, tom. 2. ſhal find more varietie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>6.</hi> Contradiction.</head>
               <p>Peter Lumbard the maſter of ſentences,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 40. <hi>diſt.</hi> 18.</note> teacheth that prieſtes onely haue power to manifeſt and declare, that men are bound, &amp; looſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſins: and therfore he is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by Doctor Allen in his booke of the power of prieſthood. I wil ſet downe their maſters reaſons: <hi>Non ergo poſtmodum per ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotem, cui confitetur, ab ira aeterna libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, à qua liberatus eſt per dominum, ex quo dixit confitebor, he is not afterward deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from aeternall vvrath by the priest, to
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:12177:74"/> whome he maketh confeſſion, from which he is deliuered by the Lord, euen then, vvhen he ſaid I will confeſſe.</hi> His ſyllogiſme is this.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>He that is deliuered by the Lord, before his confeſsion, is not abſolued by the Prieſt.</p>
                  <p>But the repentant is deliuered by the Lord himſelfe before his confeſsion:</p>
                  <p>Therefore not by the Prieſt.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Next followeth Ambroſe his teſtimonie. <hi>Verbum dei dimittit peccata, ſacerdos, &amp; iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex, ſacerdos quidem officium ſuum exhibet, ſed nullius potestatis ius exercet. The vvord of God namely Ieſus Chriſt forgiueth ſinnes being Priest, and Iudge, the Prieſt indeede doeth his duetie, but hee practiſeth not the right of any povver:</hi> To Ambroſe is adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned S. Auguſtins ſaying. <hi>Nemo tollit peccata niſi ſolus Deus: no man taketh away ſinne but onely God:</hi> Afterward in the ſame diſtinction he prooueth it, becauſe the Lord firſt clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Leapers, and then ſent them to the Prieſts. Hee likewiſe firſt raiſed Lazarus, and then offred him to the diſciples, &amp; in the end after Hieroms notable teſtimony he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth thus, <hi>Et in remitte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dis, vel in retine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:12177:74"/> culpis id iuris &amp; officii habent Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelici ſacerdotes, quod olim habebant in lege legales in curandis leproſis,</hi> The Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal prieſts haue that power and office in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing and retaining of ſiinnes which in times paſt the legall prieſtes had in curing of the lepers, nowe euery man knoweth that they did but declare them to be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>7.</hi> Contradiction.</head>
               <p>Picus Mirandula in his firſt queſtion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Chriſt his deſcent into hell, affirmeth that, <hi>Scotus in ſacris literis non parùm exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatus dicit, quod ex ſacra ſcriptura non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur, quod Christus deſcenderit ad inferos: Scotus being vvell ſtudied in the Bible tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth that it is not prooued out of the holie writte that Christ deſcended into hell:</hi> yet it is notorious to ſee how the Papiſts do luſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pull &amp; hayle the Scriptures to prooue this matter. The ſame Picus in the before named queſtion, bringeth forth Durandus teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, firſt concerning his learning, and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:12177:75"/> then ſetting downe his wordes, <hi>Videtur quod Chriſtus ſecundum animam non de ſcen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derit ad infernum, quia idem finitum non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test ſimul eſſe in diuerſis locis, ſed anima Chriſti cum eſſet creatura finita, &amp; ſtatim poſt mortem fuit in paradi ſo cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anima latro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, cui dictum est Lucae</hi> 23. <hi>hodie mecum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris in Paradiſo, ergo tunc ſaltem non potuit eſſe in miſeria. It ſhould ſeeme that Chriſt in ſoule went not dovvne into hell, becauſe the ſame finit thing ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be at one time in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places: but the ſoule of Chriſt beeing a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit creature, was by and by after death in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, with the theeves ſoule, to vvhome it vvas ſaide</hi> Luke 23. <hi>this day thou ſhalt be with me in paradiſe: therefore then it could not be in hell.</hi> Againe, <hi>Quae Chriſtus fecit, &amp; paſsus eſt in natura aſſumpta, ordinata fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt ad ſalutem humanam, ſed ad hanc non profuiſſet, quòd Chriſtus ad inferos deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſset quiaper paſsionem quam Chriſtus in hoc mundo ſuſtinuit, liberauit nos ab omni culpa &amp; poena.</hi> Thoſe things that Chriſt did, and ſuffered in his aſſumpted humane nature were ordained for mans ſaluation, but it
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:12177:75"/> furthered not this that Chriſt went into hell, becauſe by his paſsion which he ſuffred in this world, he deliuered vs from all guilt and puniſhment. The concluſion is that Chriſt deſcended not locally into hell, but by operation and effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The 8 Contradiction.</head>
               <p>Melchior Canus in his 12. booke of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon places and thirteene chapter, page 450 teacheth, that <hi>in Chriſti voluntate intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuali, (quae propriè voluntas eſt) non triſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia modo ſed ſumma &amp; maxima fuit. In Chriſts intellectuall will, which is properly vvill, there vvas not onely ſorrow but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great heauineſſe:</hi> and this he proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth thus, <hi>In hoſtia pro peccato potiſsimum deſideratur voluntatis triſtitia, ſacrificium quippe deo ſpiritus contribulatus, In the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for ſinne is deſired eſpecially the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of the will, for a troubled ſpirit is a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice vnto god,</hi> his ſyllogiſme is this.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Chriſt offered the moſt acceptable ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice vnto God.</p>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:12177:76"/>
                  <p>But the moſt acceptable ſacrifice to God is ſorow in the will: <hi>Ergo</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>Secondly he prooueth it becauſe that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt did thoſe things for vs, which doe eſpecially manifeſt his loue, but herein (namely in ſuffering in ſoule) is his loue eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially manifeſted: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Other reaſons for this purpoſe are alleadged by him, but in the ende hee concludeth, that <hi>Chriſtus</hi> was <hi>derelictus à deo, omni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> penitus destitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſolatio,</hi> that Chriſt was forſaken of god, and altogether deſtitute of all comfort. If Galuin had written ſo, how ſhould he haue beene reuiled and taunted by the papiſts? who accuſe vs of blaſphemie becauſe that we ſay he ſuffered in ſoule. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Ferus vpon the 27. of Math. goeth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and teacheth that <hi>Chriſtus deſperatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem piorum in ſe recepit,</hi> Chriſt tooke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the deſpaire of the godly. Yet nowe who knoweth not the contrarie is helde by the papiſts, namely, that <hi>Chriſtus non graui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſuppliciorum, ſed actionum pondere iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiae diuine ſatisfecit,</hi> that Chriſt ſatisfied Gods iuſtice not by ſuſtaining any grieuous
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:12177:76"/> puniſhment, but by the weight or excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of his actions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>9.</hi> Contradiction.</head>
               <p>Aquinas in his 2. 2 quaeſt. 91. <hi>artic. ſecundo, reſponſione adquartum,</hi> writeth that, <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta muſica magis movent animum ad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectationem, quam vt per ed formetur inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius bona diſpoſitio.</hi> Inſtruments of muſicke do rather ſtirre vp the minde to delight, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> frame any good diſpoſition in it, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth the Papiſts arguments brought for them <hi>In veteri Testamento vſus erat tali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um instrumentorum, tum quia populus erat magis durus, &amp; carnalis, vnde erat per hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſmodi instrumenta provocandus, ſicut &amp; per promiſsiones terrenas, tum etiam quia huiuſmodi instrumenta corporalia aliquid ſignificabant.</hi> In the olde Teſtament there was vſe of ſuch inſtruments becauſe the people were hard and carnall, whereby it
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:12177:77"/> commeth to paſſe, that they were to be exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſuch inſtruments, as by earthly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and alſo becauſe ſuch corporall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments did praeſigne ſome thing. Howe this agreeth to Bellarmines defence of them, let the Papiſts themſelues iudge. The ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas alſo in the ſame place ſaith, <hi>Nobilior modus est provocandi homines ad devotione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per doctrinam &amp; praedicationem, quàm per cantum. It is a more excellent kinde of vvay to excite and provoke the people to deuotion by doctrine and preaching, then by ſinging.</hi> And therefore <hi>praelati non debent cantibus inſiſtere ne per hoc à maioribus retrahantur. Prelates ought not to inſiſt in ſinging leaſt men by this thing ſhould be drawen from greater matters.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>10.</hi> Contradiction.</head>
               <p>The Counſel of Baſill 36. ſeſsio: holdeth that the Virgin Mary was <hi>Immunis ab omni peccato originali, free from all original ſinne:</hi> and forbiddeth all men to preach the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. So do many more Papiſts hold, yet A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:12177:77"/> prooueth the contrarie 3. <hi>part. quaeſt.</hi> 27. <hi>artic.</hi> 2. firſt becauſe that <hi>ſanctificatio non eſt niſi emundatio à peccato originali, culpa autem non potest emundari niſi per gratiam, cuius ſubiestum eſt ſola creatura rationalis. Sanstification is nothing els but a clenſing from originall ſinne, now ſinne can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be purged but onely by grace the ſubiect whereof is onely a reaſonable creature.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly becauſe, <hi>ſola creatura rationalis eſt ſuſceptiua culpae, only a reaſonable creature is capable of ſinne:</hi> if Mary had no ſinne, then ſhee ſhould haue needed no Sauiour: but Chriſt ſaued the people, and therefore Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Thus whiles the Papiſts pretende to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Mary, and ſo Chriſt, they rob Chriſt of his glorie, and honour, which is to bee Maries ſauiour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>11.</hi> Contradiction.</head>
               <p>It is held by Papiſts that in Purgatorie ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction is made to God for mans ſinnes
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:12177:78"/> but Aquinas telleth vs the contrary in his ſupplement, <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 5. <hi>artic.</hi> 3. for being vrged by this reaſon that <hi>paena purgatorii ad ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factoria pro peccato, ſed ſatisfactio habet efficaciam ex vi contritionis, ergo contritio manet poſt hanc vitam:</hi> the puniſhment of purgatorie ſatisfyeth for ſinne, but ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath his efficacy from contrition, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore contrition indureth after this life. The force of this argument driueth him to this aunſwere, <hi>paena illa quam animae in purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio ſuſtinent, non poteſt proprie dici ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio quia ſatisfactio opus meritorium requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the puniſhment which the ſoules ſuſtaine in purgatory cannot properly be called ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, becauſe ſatisfaction requireth merit.</hi> But there is no merit in purgatory: therefore no ſatisfaction. And if his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the ſame place be good that there is no ſorrowe for ſinnes in purgatorie, becauſe <hi>ſacramenta non manent poſt hanc vitam, the ſacraments indure not after this life.</hi> Then is therfore no ſatisfaction in purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, becauſe ſatisfaction is a part of their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of penance, as well as contrition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:12177:78"/>
               <head>The <hi>12.</hi> Contradiction.</head>
               <p>Aquinas in his third <hi>part. quaeſt.</hi> 25. <hi>articu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo</hi> 3. holdeth that, <hi>Imago Chriſti eſt adoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da adoratione latriae. The Image of Chriſt is to be worſhipped with the ſame worſhip that Chriſt himſelfe:</hi> and prooueth it clarkly (I warrant you) out of Ariſtotle his booke <hi>de memoria.</hi> I will not ſtand to ſet downe his reaſon beeing fully anſwered by Picus Mira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dula, that great learned man, to whome I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the reader concerning this queſtion. The contrary is held by many Papiſts, as may be ſeene in Picus before named, and in Bellarmine himſelfe. Behold vnto what I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie Papiſts are growen, to worſhippe a creature with the ſame honour which is due to the Creator himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>13.</hi> Contradiction.</head>
               <p>In the Cenſure of Colon we are taught<note place="margin">
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 89.</note>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:12177:79"/> a certaine vaine kinde of difference betwixt faith and hope. Faith (ſaith that Cenſure) is of generall propoſitions, as, <hi>Quicunque cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diderit, &amp; baptizatus fuerit, ſalvus erit:</hi> Whoſoeuer beleeueth, and is baptized, ſhall be ſaued. But it is not of theſe propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: <hi>ergo advitam aeternam ingrediar, aut mihi peccata remiſsa ſunt.</hi> I ſhall enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life euerlaſting, or my ſinnes are forgiuen me.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 139.</note> The Catechiſme of Colon teacheth contrariwiſe, that <hi>ad iustificationem requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur, vt ſinguli credant ſibi remiſsa pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta per Christum:</hi> It is requiſite to iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that euery one beleeueth that his ſinnes are forgiuen him by Chriſt;<note place="margin">Serm. <hi>1.</hi> de Eunuch.</note> and prooueth the ſame by that excellent teſtimonie of Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard. It is not ſufficient to beleeue that thou canſt not haue remiſsion of ſinnes, but by Gods mercie: and thou canſt haue any good thing except God giueth thee it: and that thou canſt not deſerue eternall life by any workes, beſides theſe which are but <hi>initiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fidei,</hi> the beginning of faith. <hi>Hoc etiam ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum, vt credas quòd per ipſum tibi pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata condonentur;</hi> this moreouer is to be
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:12177:79"/> added, that thou beleeueſt that thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee by God; and this is the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie which the holy Ghoſt doth aſſure thee of in thy heart, ſaying, thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee. Out of this teſtimonie of Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, we may gather, that to thinke of the Popiſh faith the contrarie is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the Papiſts, namely, that no man is to beleeue the forgiueneſſe of his ſinnes, which doctrine is plainely confuted by their owne Catechiſme, as we ſaide.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>14.</hi> Contradictions.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Spes</hi> (ſaith the Maſter of ſentences) <hi>est cum fiducia expectatio futurae beatitudinis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>diſt.</hi> 26</note> 
                  <hi>veniens ex dei gratia, &amp; meritis praeceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus:</hi> Hope is an expectation of the bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to come with an affiance proceeding of Gods grace, and our precedent merits: yet the ſame Catechiſme of Colon, pag. 138. and 140. placeth all our affiance in God his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull promiſe. But no more of this contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:12177:80"/> becauſe I haue ſpoken of it in the reaſon of diſſolute, and diſcomfortable do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>15.</hi> Contradiction.</head>
               <p>The ſame Catechiſme teacheth out of Bernard that we are iuſtified onely by faith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 141.</note> 
                  <hi>hoc est non per merita propria, ſed per miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricordiam dei, quam ſola fides, accipit, &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendit,</hi> that is, none by our owne merits, but by Gods mercie, which onely faith doth apprehend. What Proteſtant teacheth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny otherwiſe? Bernard his words are theſe, <hi>Quiſquis pro peccatis compunctus, eſurit, &amp; ſitit iustitiam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Serm. <hi>22</hi> in Cantic.</note> 
                  <hi>credat in te, qui iustificas im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium, &amp; ſolam iustificatus per fidem, pacem habebit apud Deum.</hi> Whoſoeuer is pricked in his heart for his ſinnes, and hungreth and thirſteth after righteouſnes, let him beleeue in thee that iuſtifieth the vngodly man, and beeing iuſtified by onely faith, he ſhall haue peace with God. Here I might haue alſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged the teſtimonie of Albertus Pighius for iuſtification by imputatiue righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. The ſame Catechiſme alſo fol. 85. tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:12177:80"/> that iuſtifying faith is vnſeparable from hope and charitie, and anſwereth the place of the 1. to the Corinth. and 13. chap. by the teſtimonies of Chryſoſtome, Theophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lact, Baſill, and Ambroſe: how well the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts agree in theſe 2. points with this their Catechiſme, let their owne writings wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>16.</hi> Contradiction.</head>
               <p>Scotus in the firſt booke of ſentences, and 27. diſtinct. prooueth that good workes deſerue, <hi>opera merentur tantùm ex pacto,</hi> works deſerue onely by reaſon of God his couenant and promiſe. His argument is this, <hi>Meritum non eſt niſivbi est dignum: at non est dignu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſpectu intrinſecarum actionu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> there is no deſert but where there is a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines: but in reſpect of our inward actions, there is no worthineſſe: <hi>ergo.</hi> His aſſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is thus prooued, <hi>tunc enim deus non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit non retribuere beatitudinem,</hi> if there were any worthineſſe in the works them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, then God is bounde to giue vnto them happineſſe and bleſſedneſſe: but God is not bounde. <hi>Ergo.</hi> Reade Bellarmine
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:12177:81"/> in his 5. booke of iuſtification, and thou ſhalt not onely finde Scotus his opinion miſliked, whoſe argument is vnanſwerable, but Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randus alſo reprehended by Bellarmine, ſuch is the harmony betwixt Papiſts in ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all points of religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>17.</hi> Contradiction.</head>
               <p>Roffenſis in his 32. article againſt Luther, agreeth with Luther about veniall ſinne, namely that none is veniall of it own nature, but only by gods mercy, <hi>Quod peccatum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niale ſolùm ex dei miſericordia veniale ſit, in hoc tecum ſentio:</hi> that a veniall ſinne is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly veniall through Gods mercy, therein I do agree vnto thee. Read more Papiſts of Rof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſis his minde in Bellarmine <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat. cap.</hi> 4. yet we know that Aquinas &amp; ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally all Papiſts do teach otherwiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>18.</hi> Contradiction.</head>
               <p>Aquinas in his <hi>prima</hi> 2. 109. <hi>quaest. artic.</hi> 6. teacheth that man without grace, cannot <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:12177:81"/> peccatum,</hi> auoide and eſchew ſinne; and anſwereth three reaſons brought againſt this opinion. The firſt reaſon is thus framed. He that cannot auoide ſinne but ſinneth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily, ſinneth not at all. The ſecond argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is this, It followe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h of this opinion that reprehenſions are needleſſe. Thirdly, &amp; laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Eccleſ. 15. it is ſaid, that <hi>ante hominem est vita, &amp; mors,</hi> before man is life and death. Theſe three arguments are all anſwered by Aquinas, and yet they are the papiſts pillers of free-wil as euery man knoweth: if it were needfull I might quote the authors that vſe them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>19.</hi> Contradiction.</head>
               <p>Alexander de Hales <hi>parte</hi> 4. <hi>quaest.</hi> 24. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth that confirmation was inſtituted by Chriſt: his reaſons are theſe two, <hi>Quia Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus quando inſtituit aliquod Sacramentum, determinat elementum,</hi> when Chriſt doth inſtitute any ſacrament, hee determineth of the element, and matter of the Sacrament, but hee hath not done ſo in this Sacrament:
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:12177:82"/> 
                  <hi>Ergo</hi> it was not inſtituted of him. Secondly, <hi>in Sacramentis vna forma est, in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments there is one forme of words,</hi> but in this there is not one forme of wordes; for in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers churches they haue diuers formes: <hi>Ergo</hi> it was not inſtituted of Chriſt. Hence it may be concluded that it is no ſacrament, becauſe all Sacraments were ordained by Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, as Aquinas holdeth 3. <hi>parte, quaest.</hi> 72. <hi>art.</hi> 1. <hi>reſp. adprimum,</hi> where alſo wee may ſee that ſome held, (as Alexander de Hales holdeth) namely, that it was not inſtituted of Chriſt, and by conſequent it is no Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>20.</hi> Contradiction.</head>
               <p>The Contradictions about the Sacrament of the alter, and reall preſence are ſo manie, that I will not enter into them, becauſe I eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew tediouſneſſe, onely I will ſet downe Aquinas his opinion in his ſupplement, 83. <hi>quaeſt. art.</hi> 3. <hi>reſponſione ad quartum:</hi> namely that on body cannot bee locally in two pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at one time, for it implyeth a Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:12177:82"/> but now the Papiſts care not for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction: ſo they may make the bodie of Chriſt preſent locally in the Sacrament. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more Contradictions might I haue ſet downe, as namely the certaine knowledge that a man is in grace, and ſuch like taught by Papiſts, but it ſhall ſuffice to haue proued that in the weightieſt points of controuerſie the Papiſts are on our ſide. Let them now bragge no more of vnitie, for the ſpirite of diſſention is ſowen amongſt them. Did euer the Caluiniſts teach the weightieſt points of poperie, as the papiſts do the greateſt opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Caluiniſme? I know they doe not. Thus leauing this reaſon to the indifferent reader to iudge of, euery man may ſee what cauſe there is to diſclaime and renounce the Romiſh religion.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="reason">
            <pb n="144" facs="tcp:12177:83"/>
            <head>The twelue reaſon of the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of many things taught &amp; held in Poperie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or aſmuch as in one of my former reaſons I haue by ſufficient teſtimonies proued the practiſe of the primitiue Church to bee repugnant to Poperie in many weightie matters, I ſhal not need to be long in the Original of the Romiſh religion; certaine it is that it was not all hatched at once,<note place="margin">Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. de p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>p.</note> and that it it not a thing neceſſarie to ſhew the beginning of euerie point in pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſeing that <hi>ipſa Papistarum doctrina cum Apostolis comparata ex diuerſitate, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarietate ſua pronunciabit, neque Apoſtoli alicuius authoris eſſe, neque Apostolici. The Popiſh doctrine it ſelfe being compared with the Apoſtles will by the varietie and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie that is in it, pronounce that neither
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:12177:83"/> Apoſtle, nor any Apostolicall man was the au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thor of it.</hi> Notwithſtanding both becauſe it helpeth much for the ſatisfying of ſome, and alſo becauſe diuerſe abuſes are noted by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, I will ſet downe ſome things concerning the Originall of poperie: and firſt heare what Bucchingerus an arch Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt in his Eccleſiaſtical hiſtory writeth, pag. 217. <hi>Res eſt plena horroris vel legere, vel me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſſe, tantam tyrannidem, inter ſe exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuiſſe mutuò Pontifices Romanos: ô quantum degenerarunt à maioribus ſuis! &amp; fieri non potuit in tanta crudelitate, vt pietatis Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianae ratio haberetur ne cui mirum ſit inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim, ſiqui abuſus &amp; perverſae opiniones in Eccleſiam irrepſêrunt.</hi> It is a thing full of horror either to reade or to remember the great tyranny the Biſhops of Rome haue practiſed one toward another: ô howe are they degenerate from their aunceſtoures! and it cannot be that in ſuch crueltie their ſhould be had any regard of Chriſtian piety: let no man then marueile if ſome abuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and badde opinions haue crept into the church. Loe here three things noted by a Papiſt him
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:12177:84"/> ſelfe. Firſt the cruelty of the Romiſh Biſhops, 2. their degeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from their aunceſtours, and thirdly that certaine badde opinions by this meanes are crept into the Church. For proofe of this laſt point, I will beginne with purgatory, becauſe that it hath warmed the popes kitchin. Concerning which let Rof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſis a papiſt ſpeake, <hi>artic.</hi> 18. <hi>contra aſsert. Lutheri, fer in ini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſed Graecis etiam adhunc vſque diem, non creditum eſt purgatorium eſſe: legat quicunque velit Graecorum veteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commentarios &amp; nullum (quantum opinor) aut quàm rariſsimum de purgatorio ſermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem inveniet. Sed neque Latini ſimul om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes huius rei veritatem concepêrunt,</hi> &amp; rur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, <hi>non abſque maxima ſpiritus ſancti diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſatione factum est, quod poſt tot annorum curricula, purgatorii fides, &amp; indulgentiaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſus, ab orthodoxis generatim ſit recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, quandiu nulla fuit de purgatorio cura, nemo quaeſivit indulgentias, nam ex illo pendet omnis indulgentiarum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtimatio.</hi> The Greeks to this daie doe not beleeue that there is purgatory, reade who liſt the Commentaries of the auncient Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:12177:84"/> and he ſhall finde either very ſeldome mention of purgatory, or none at all. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did the Latin Church conceiue the trueth of this thing at one time. <hi>And againe,</hi> neither was it done without the great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of the holy ghoſt that after ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares, Catholikes both beleeued purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and receiued the vſe of pardon gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, ſo long as there was no care of purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, no man ſought for pardons, for of it dependeth all the aeſtimation that we haue of pardons. Out of this teſtimony I gather firſt that the Greeke Church acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no purgatory. Secondly that the auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Latin Church did not beleeue it. Thirdly, that theſe opinions grewe by little and little in the Church. Fourthly and laſtly that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons depende vpon purgatorie, and ſo are newe deuiſes of mans braine. Therefore let pardons &amp; purgatory pickpurſe goe. From purgatory I paſſe to the Popes primacy, which is an after invention (as I prooue out of Socrates in the 7. booke of his Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall hiſtorie, and the 11. chap.) <hi>Epiſcopatus Romanus non aliter atque Alexandrinus,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:12177:85"/> quaſiextra ſacerdotii fines egreſſus ad ſaecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larem principatum iam erat ante delapſus. The Biſhops of Rome and Alexandria going beyond the limits of prieſthood, vvent into a ſecular &amp; worldly dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> For proofe of this, when Victor [as Euſebius writeth <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 23. Eccleſiaſtic. hiſtor.] would haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated the Churches of Aſia, he was reſiſted by Iraeneus. To paſſe ouer that, Policarpus would not yeeld to Amcetus. We know that before Boniface the firſt no Biſhop of Rome was called vniuerſal biſhop. Laſtly as teſtifieth <hi>(Faſciculus temporum) anno</hi> 704, in Gregory the ſecond his daies, <hi>Domini Papae plus ſolito erant in temporali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, The popes grewe more in temporall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters then they vvere vvoont.</hi> Thirdly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning miniſters marriage, Bucchingerus (before named) ſaith, pag. 104, that <hi>Calixtus nemini in ſacris ordinib. constituto, licere ſuperducere vxorem, conubialique vinculo ſe conſtringere ſtatuit.</hi> decreed that no man being in holy orders, might marry a wife &amp; bind himſelfe with the marriage bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Maierius in his book, <hi>de differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiis ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>matum,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:12177:85"/> pag.</hi> 136. profeſſeth his ignorance in this point, namely, who did firſt prohibite it, yet ſaith, that ſome referre it to Calixtus vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe ridiculous, and barbarous verſes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>O bone Calixte nunc omnis clerus odit te,</l>
               <l>Olim presbyteri poterant vxoribus vti,</l>
               <l>Hoc destruxisti quando tu Papa fuisti.</l>
               <l>Ergo tuum festum nunquam celebratur honestum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>O Calixtus thou art hated of all the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, prieſts might marry in times paſt, which thou didſt take away being Pope, therefore thy feſtiuall day is not honorably celebrated. O hers referre it to Syricius the Pope: cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is, that it was not from the Apoſtles, (as is proued out of Gratian: <hi>part.</hi> 1. <hi>diſtinct.</hi> 56. <hi>Cenomanenſem.) Coniugia ſacerdotibus ante prohibitionem vbique erant licita, &amp; in Orientali Eccleſia vſque hodiè licere pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur, Mariage of miniſters was lawfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the prohibition thereof, and in the East churches they are lawfull vnto this day.</hi> See Polydore Virgill in his fift booke <hi>de inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toribus rerum,</hi> when it was reſtrained in the Weſt churches. Howſoeuer it is not certen
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:12177:86"/> who firſt reſtrained the marriage of mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, yet it is certaine that, Calixtus <hi>instituit ieiunium quatuor temporum, appointed the fast of the foure times,</hi> namely in March, May, September, and December, Bucchinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus in the ſame place. Fiftly, Innocentius the firſt, <hi>anno</hi> 404. <hi>statuit, quòd non ſolum preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteri, ſedomnes Christiani deberent vngi oleo infirmorum,</hi> decreed that not onely Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, but al Chriſtians ought to be annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the oyle of the ſick. <hi>Faſciculus tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum, folio</hi> 50. <hi>Ergo,</hi> extreame vnction is no Sacrament, being inuented, and deuiſed by a Pope. Sixtly, <hi>anno</hi> 654. <hi>Feſtum purificationis inſtitutum fuit,</hi> the feaſt of the purification of Marie was inſtituted. <hi>Faſciculus temporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, folio</hi> 55. Seuenthly, <hi>anno</hi> 654. <hi>Vitellianus ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum organorum instituit,</hi> Pope Vitellian or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined Organes in the church. <hi>Faſciculus temp. fol.</hi> 60. Eightly, <hi>anno</hi> 614. <hi>Bonifacius inſtituit feſtum omnium ſanctorum,</hi> ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the feaſt of al Saints. <hi>Faſciculus temp. fol.</hi> 58. Ninthly, <hi>anno</hi> 484. <hi>Festum viſitationis Mariae institutum fuit ab Vrbano,</hi> The feaſt of the viſitation of Marie was ordained by
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:12177:86"/> Vrbanus. <hi>Faſciculus temp fol.</hi> 86. Tenthly, <hi>Festi dies instituti ſunt à Foelice primo,</hi> feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall daies were inſtituted of Faelix the firſt. Bucchingerus 130. pag. Eleuenthly, <hi>Pelagius horas canonicas inſtituit,</hi> Pelagius appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted canonicall howers. <hi>Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pag.</hi> 167. Twelfly, <hi>Gregorius primus Letaniam auxit,</hi> Gregory the firſt increaſed the Letanie. <hi>Idem pag</hi> 173. And becauſe I might abound in theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, read this author, and thou ſhalt finde the Originall, of euery thing almoſt in their Maſſe: the worſhipping of Images was not concluded (as Alfonſus witneſſeth) before the Councell of Nice. Tranſubſtantion in the Laterane Councell was determined vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Pope Iulius. Iuell in the defence of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie pag. 35. the cupp was taken from the people by the Councell of Conſtance. But theſe ſhall ſuffice to ſhew the Originall of poperie: by them euery man may iudge of the reſt, neither let any man ſay theſe are tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles. For the Popes primacie, purhatorie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of miniſters, extreame vnction, images, tranſubſtantiation, and the cuppe are matters of exceeding great moment. And for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:12177:87"/> (chriſtian Reader) I ſaye with the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator, in his 2. booke <hi>de natura Deorum, ſi ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula haec te non mouent, vniuerſa tamen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſe connexa, &amp; coniuncta mouere debent.</hi> If euery one of theſe ſeuerally can not moue and perſwade thee to relinquiſh poperie, yet all of them ioyned and coupled together ought to perſwade thee.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12177:87"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
